All right.
In this
lecture we're going to go over containers.
What they are.
A little history behind them to see how
they've evolved into what they are today.
So, first off, there's a Trivial Pursuit
question everyone should know,
and always get right.
What's older containers
or virtual machines?
The answer might surprise
people as containers really took off
in the mid, 2000.
Actually closer to 2010.
So when they really kind of took off,
but before that, they,
they were actually established really
early on in the Unix, operating systems
with filesystem isolation
and with something called jails.
And,
they turned in the millennium in 2000,
in, freebie, FreeBSD and also in
Solaris and Sun OS even
had some inklings of, of these things.
But the problem with containers back
in those days is
they were still very difficult to use.
And, even even in the early days,
when the Linux Foundation took over
namespaces and C groups and L,
c, which combined both of them in 2008,
it was still,
not super easy to use,
not until Docker really came on to,
the it came into the ecosystem
and made it easy to use.
And once that happened,
developers flocked to it in droves
because it made it easy to stand up
applications
had a complete OS that I could,
put into a container,
right into a little package
that I could easily deploy it,
it could run its stuff and then,
you know, tear down very quickly.
And now that was one of the,
the huge benefits of,
Docker containers that made it so easy.
And the reason it,
it kind of overtook, VMs,
and it kind of took a little bit of time,
but it overtook VMs
is because they were so lightweight
and they came up so quickly,
so understanding kind of that background
kind of gives you an idea with software
engineering and computer science,
what we tend to see is
if we can make something easier,
take a complex concept
and make it easier to use,
people will flock to it.
More than likely.
And that's really
what happened with, Docker containers.
And why it really kind of just took off
and it took over the world.
All right.
So the isolation, mechanisms
that are used, are really interesting.
Let's start with namespaces first.
So namespaces gave me the ability
to isolate
different parts of the operating system
with process IDs, network mounts, UTI,
all this stuff together, to give me
isolation and some, some security.
So, it it wouldn't allow users
to see other people's, information.
I could isolate all these, processes
and everything into a specific namespace.
Then came control groups,
where I now started looking
beyond just the user data and started
looking more into the operating system
where I had, control of CPU, memory,
IO network limits.
I could start having these control groups
that could control kind of,
the hardware side of things.
And then, we had you
you combine all that with file systems,
and this gave me a quick way
to, to get things,
launched and get things going.
So the idea behind containers
and the union file systems, where
I'm combining things together
to create a new image,
meant that I could start out very quickly
by reusing different layers
in, in containers
between different containers.
But the total, container itself
was unique, so it made it very, very fast.
So let's take a look at a container image.
Right. A container image.
And this is hard for people at first.
But a container image contains
everything that's needed in order
to run the application in, in, in a file
or a, it's an interesting thing.
It's a layered file
for no, for no better word.
And it always starts with a base image.
Some of the most popular ones out there.
Alpine being a very small image.
Very, very small.
And this is really good
if you have memory
limitations
or if you're running out at the edge.
It's very small and very compact,
and it by default doesn't
include everything.
You have to include
every single package that you need.
This is great for security as well, right?
As you as you're not having extra weight
coming around, with the system.
Then I another,
one that I have is ubuntu,
which everyone knows ubuntu
that's worked in Linux.
Right.
And there's different flavors of ubuntu.
You can do a lightweight, lightweight
ubuntu or go bigger.
Then what happens from that base
image is I build things on top of,
I install different packages that I need,
and then
I can take, let's say,
a base image of alpine.
I can install Node.js on there, and
I can call that a Node.js alpine image.
So now any, program that needs Node.js,
I can just take that image and use it.
So this, this thing keeps building
on top of each other.
And one way to protect it
from being changed is by,
having immutable artifacts in there
and creating
a, hash or sha sha 256, does a great job
so that I can be guaranteed
that the layer that I say it is
that I can check it against the hash
and it'll work.
Now, these layers or images,
of containers that I have out there,
I can store in repository
so I can use them over and over again.
And one of the true benefits of this,
layered approach of the images
is because the images are built
through layers.
If I have 100 different images,
but they all have the base
layer of, the alpine operating system,
the base image,
I only have to download that base image
once because the other things are are kind
of, sucked in at, runtime.
So I'm not carrying around all, of,
all of that information.
I'm guaranteed, immutable artifacts,
immutable layers, throughout there.
So I just add on to what's needed.
This is one of the things
that makes Docker, faster than like a VM,
where I'm taking a snapshot of everything
and it's all coming in there.
Now, there's some benefits to VMs.
If I can take a snapshot
of a running application,
I save all the state I can migrate.
I can migrate VMs around
because they save state containers.
No save state
unless I take a snapshot of it.
But even then, it's not saving all
the registers and everything else on it.
Then I normally have a run in there.
So that's that's a major difference
that you should understand.
But these registries,
the most popular one out
there is Docker Hub,
but there's several others out there.
Even GitHub is starting
and has y'all years ago
actually started, hosting a Docker
containers or Docker images.
I guess it's the right, way to put it.
Okay,
one of the things I've already talked
about is the portability aspect.
So because it's carrying
the whole operating system with it
and the applications, I can easily build
this image once
and I can spin it up anywhere.
And that's really cool, right?
Because everything's contained inside
that bundle, that I need.
And, it makes it very easy
for me to declare these are using
something called a Docker file.
So I can create through code,
I can create these images,
that I can use over and over again,
which is, which is awesome.
Where VM a VM takes a current,
running a machine
because it's saving state.
State. I take a snapshot of that.
So, VMs are much more difficult
to code up
like I can with a container where I can be
very explicit about what's going into
that image that I get started, including
configuration files, the whole gamut.
All right.
The other really cool thing about,
containers is the ability
to spin them up in milliseconds
instead of seconds or minutes.
For VMs, even pretty large,
containers can spin up very quickly,
especially if I've spun them up before,
because those layers are already on that
machine and I can get things
going, much quicker.
The other thing is, is I can install
a lot more containers onto a box
and I can a VM. Why?
You're right, they're sharing
some of the same memory space,
under the containers,
specifically those base layers,
at spin up time, they're,
they're saving those, which,
which means
I've got really low overhead, for those.
And there's no, there's no,
guest OS kernel like I have in, in VMs.
Right. Everything's contained.
It's very low overhead there.
Now, some people have said, can I run a,
an alpine container on a windows box?
And the answer to that is kind of sorta,
because containers right now
are primarily running on Unix, boxes or
flavors of Unix like Linux or,
whistle to, whistle to things like that.
So it can run on a windows box,
but you are actually running it in a VM
that's running Linux.
So there you go.
All right.
Some security concerns with, containers.
So you want to make sure
that when you are running containers
that you are dropping any capabilities
you do not need in that container,
because that opens up, the attack
surface of that container,
make sure that you're running as non-root.
That when you spin up, your container
in your image, you can define
which user you're running as
and make sure
that you use a lot of the hardening
and vulnerability scanning techniques
that are out there today.
Right.
There's lots of options out there
to scan, containers
and even, Docker
itself has some of that scanning
capability in there.
Another, great technique
here is to sign your images
to make sure that you are getting them
from a reliable source
and that they're not coming,
with some malicious code in them.
So this is kind of been been great
for the Docker ecosystem,
because you can make them even more secure
than what we've seen
with some of the VM images
that are out there today.
Okay.
Lots of standards out there.
There's been, really interesting battles
in in running images out there.
But from that, the easiest way to put it
is there's a Docker engine
that that's been around for a long time.
Probably one of the most popular
container D
is an underlying,
what's the right word?
I wouldn't call it a hypervisor,
but it's running the containers and CRI.
Oh, these are light, lightweight runtimes
for the,
containers.
The images to start running and then OCI
are image and runtime, specifications.
Go ahead and and research those some more
if you want to learn more about them.
There's quite an interesting history
behind each one of these
in kind of the standards battle,
that that went on behind
some of these, are actually quite
interesting if you're if you're interested
in learning some of the computer
science history behind it.
All right.
So we've got individual containers
and we are going to talk more
about orchestration needs
and what comes next.
But simple.
Right.
Other gun orchestration needs
for containers I need to schedule them.
I need to scale them up.
I need to be able to discover
individual containers
and what they provide, because people
are using them as microservices,
but they do one specific things.
I also need a lot of times
I need some configuration
for all my containers that are the same,
that I can pass in at runtime,
or maybe secrets, maybe their passwords
or tokens that are needed in order
for that container
to talk to another container through, TSL
or one of the other protocols
where I need tokens
being passed or certification
certs being passed around.
And then I also need the ability
for self-healing and rollouts and health
checks, so that if a container does fail,
that a new one can take its place.
Remember, containers tend to not store
well, they don't store, state.
So I need to store that state somewhere.
And if I even starting up
a new container, it needs to know
whether it's a stateless container
or whether I need to pick up
for where I left off by storing those in,
in some kind of storage.
Right.
Some kind of, persistent store.
All right.
So best practices,
keep your containers small,
make sure that they have
a single responsibility for the image.
I've seen some of these images
have everything in them,
which is great when you're doing
development and things like that.
But for production,
they become kind of big and unwieldy,
and you lose some of the flexibility that
you want, for deploying and scalability
and all those things that we look for
in a microservice architecture.
Multi-stage builds, you want to make sure
that you are building
things in, in stages
and take advantage of that layering
that you have instead of having one
big command in one of the steps,
have multiple steps in there.
So if you do make a change to it,
you're not rebuilding everything.
You're only building that one layer.
And take advantage of,
take advantage of CI, CD pipelines
in automating
the build of your of your, containers
that you have out there.
And here's another great hint.
And a lot of times developers
miss this one, I do I miss this one a lot.
You can set
resource limits on your container.
So if you get, the infamous
while one for loop
in one of your applications
that you can limit how much CPU and memory
that's going to take, or even worse, in a,
while one for loop is a while,
one Malak Falk loop,
that will throw you for a loop.
You'll chew up all the CPU
and memory really quick,
but with a container,
I can limit how much it can actually take.
All right, go out there and explore
more containers.
There's a lot.
It's a very cool technology.
Dive into it some more and play around
with Docker files.
And don't forget some of these
best practices that we've talked about.
This will help you when you start
deploying
more and more into,
your cloud architectures.