Okay.
Let's talk about Ansible in this lecture.
So Ansible is in éaC
and infrastructure as coding tool.
And we're going to go over it
and see how I can use it.
I would say it's you.
It's very useful.
But it's not the only tool out there.
So understanding its pluses and minuses,
would be very important for understanding,
the best use cases for you.
So it's an open source, automation tool
for configuration management,
as I already talked about for Isac.
It utilizes an agent, lists,
push model based over SSH.
So I don't need an agent running
on the end in order to do things.
And it has the concept of playbooks,
which are all Yaml based.
So this is all defining
the desired end state.
So it's imperative, not declarative.
I don't declare the individual steps,
I just define the desired end
state that I want to get to.
Okay.
Key concepts that we need to understand.
Control node.
That's where the machine
where you install and running Ansible.
This is the machine that you're
going to use to control
all the other nodes in your cluster.
Right. Those are the managed nodes
that are out there.
These are the target servers
where you want to install
or spin up VMs or,
you know, whatever,
whatever the case may be.
Okay.
All right. Inventory.
Inventory is a file.
It's an Ini file or Yaml file,
that lists the managed hosts or groups.
So I can I can target a whole group
saying, hey, I need you to update all of,
your configurations in web, for example.
Then it'll hit all the hosts
in that group or in DB in this case,
just the one, host that's there.
All right
then, I've got the concept of modules.
Modules are reusable units of work,
or of n states for example.
Yum apt copy template.
These are all, reusable units.
So I can have a module
that I'm doing all that with.
And then the next one is playbooks.
So a playbook is a Yaml file
that describes
the orchestration tasks
in the place that I have.
So I can say
here are the tasks that I need in order
to get to this specific, state
that I'm looking for.
Yeah. Right.
All right.
And then we talk about, arbok and roles.
So I have roles in, in Ansible as well.
And these are a structured, collection
of tasks, file handlers,
templates, defaults, whatever the case may
be, I can bundle those into roles.
I want to parameterize
my Ansible playbooks,
so I so I can reuse them
for lots of different things just by
having different variables or parameters
that I'm passing into different inventory.
And it increases, reusability,
dramatically.
And then I also have handlers in here.
So we have something is happening.
A notification, is sent.
I know what to do in case of those,
different events that are being,
sent out, like, I need to restart a server
after configuration change
and things like that.
Okay.
Next architecture and workflow. So,
first thing, the way that I work through
this is I write
an inventory targeting the different hosts
or groups that I need.
Then I write a playbook.
Then I can define roles
if I need to for a modular structure.
And then I go ahead and I run that Ansible
playbook against that inventory.
So I take that playbook and say,
apply this playbook to the
this inventory that I have here.
And you can specify, what,
what machines in your inventory
that you're targeting in your playbook.
So, the ansible engine is what connects,
ssh to each of the hosts
that are out there,
and it transfers a small Python module,
and executes it on, on the other side.
Right. So that's what's actually doing.
So I'm ssh ING in a Python module
goes over there and installs and starts,
gathering the current, state of things.
And then it also gathers
results and reuses connections,
and it supports success and failure
and things like that.
So it's kind of sneaky in that,
we see it's agent lists,
but it's actually putting
a little agent out there
to handle all the communication
while it's doing the work.
So it's not just a push and forget.
It is a push and reply, type of,
for all right.
Some inventory examples here.
So it's typically in in AI.
And I feel that it can be in a Yaml file
as well.
In this case I've got application servers
and a database server.
And I can specify
the user that I want it to run under.
On those
when I'm installing, things in there.
All right.
Here's a Yaml example of the same thing
where I've got,
a web hosts and DB host.
I can say give me everyone.
So there's, there's an example
of the same thing for inventory.
Let's take a high level
look at a playbook structure.
Again, as I said before,
it is all in Yaml.
So in this case the name of the playbook
is configure web Servers.
I'm going to run it on the web host.
As you notice here, I did not specify
the individual host but the host group.
This gives me the ability
to put different,
inventory against it, as long as it has
the groups in there that I need,
I can target different machines.
Right.
And then I've got variables coming in.
I've got tasks that need to be performed.
Install nginx or.
And then the second task
there's deploy configuration template
for nginx.
And then I've got handlers in here
like I've got a restart engine jinx.
If I get a restart
then I know exactly how to restart it.
Simple simple playbook.
All right.
If I'm defining roles, I can define roles.
And based off of the different roles,
I can have different playbooks
for those roles. Right.
So in this case, I've got a web server,
I've got the defaults in, in my main,
I've got my handlers in in there,
I've got metadata, I've got tasks
that need to run.
And so I would have one for a web server,
I would have one for, a database server
or maybe my,
oh, let's call it port forwarder,
whatever the case may be.
Right?
Or maybe my message broker or whatever
the case may be, so I can establish
it gives me a way of hierarchically
establishing, my playbooks.
Okay.
Some common commands that will help me
when I'm working with Ansible is,
if I want to ping all the hosts,
make sure that I can talk to each other,
I can easily do that with a ping command
against the whole inventory.
I can add, ad hoc module.
I can run like, uptime.
Tell me what your uptime is.
By running a shell command,
I can check syntax of a Yaml file
to make sure I have the right syntax for.
I go off and try and run it.
I can do a dry run,
which will make sure that
I have everything in order,
especially when I'm passing in variables.
It all spit out what everything would be
if it were to actually run.
I can list the tasks
that are in a playbook,
and then I can gather facts about a
inventory set up so I can see.
Here's all my inventory.
Tell me everything about, setting this up
and whether it's going to,
adhere to the playbook or not.
Okay.
That's practices, as we've talked
about with Isaac in the lecture.
If you haven't listened to that, go back
and listen to the lecture.
It's more generalized.
But first off, I can use version control
to control my playbooks,
and inventory and roles.
I want to store my secrets.
These are my keys.
So I can access in an ansible vault.
It's encrypted Yaml file.
Keep everything,
so restart that into potency
so that if I run the same command over
and over again,
I get the same results,
even if it's, already running.
So that's important, right?
Try and make sure that
I don't have any adverse effects
when I'm running multiple times.
I'll make sure you're structuring
your code with roles and includes
statements for clarity so that I can
understand what things are used for,
and use the handlers for service restarts
and configuration changes.
So I'm not stuck in these weird states
where I push a configuration out,
but the service needs to restart
in order to take advantage of that.
And then, you can leverage, Ansible Galaxy
for community roles.
So take a look at Ansible
Galaxy that's out there.
All right.
In summary,
hey, Ansible is a really cool tool.
Yaml based.
So if you don't know Yaml,
you should learn Yaml.
It's a pretty simple language.
A lot of the generative
AI tools out there can help create,
a lot of this stuff for you,
as the syntax may become a little
and daunting to know everything at first.
But by mastering these things,
you're going to be able to automate,
complex workflows
and before it would take you hours to do,
can now take you minutes to
do and to do it repeatedly.