In this lecture
we're going to go over message brokers,
why they're used and what they're good for
and the high level architecture of them.
So a message broker
when you think about it is a middleware
of decoupled asynchronous communication.
Very valuable for large scalability
durability routing load that there's a
there's a lot of benefits to them,
but they can be complex.
But the key element of them is
that there's something that produces data
and there's something that consumes data,
and there's something in the middle
that is going to broker how the data from
the producer is getting to the consumer.
The consumers and producers
don't necessarily
need to even know about each other,
just that the data is,
going to be delivered
somehow through the broker.
That's the whole idea behind it.
So why would we want to use a message
broker
primarily decoupling of the producers
in the consumers.
This is highly valuable
if you have highly scalable systems,
or if you have systems
that are undergoing a lot of change,
or if I have a certain,
or a lot of different consumers
that can be consuming the same data
but doing something different with it.
And same thing.
If I have a lot of,
producers that are producing data
from different sources,
but producing the same type of data,
that could be very valuable as well.
Of course, like in most of,
computer science,
we model the real world
when it comes to doing these things.
So it's just like a normal broker
that you would have out there,
whether it's a commodity exchange broker
or a house, a housing broker.
There's lots of different things
that you can, correlate this to.
It does have a lot of really great
benefits
like scalability, reliability.
There can be some advanced
routing and transformation, by the broker
and even traffic
shaking, shaping and, rate
limiting
so that I don't overwhelm, consumers.
So it's a great tool to look at
popular message
broking platforms out there.
Maybe you've heard of some of these rabbit
in MQ Kafka,
which is probably one of the most popular
ones,
active MQ Artemus.
Zero.
Cuz another one is AWS
SQS and Google Pubsub.
There's lots of different ones out there.
They all have their pluses and minuses.
But you should, easily investigate
which one is best for your architecture.
I would not put one of the more complex
ones on a simple architecture.
Make sure that you're using the right tool
for the right problem
space that you have.
Common
message patterns that we see out there.
The first one is like, point to point
where
this is not a normal message broker.
Right?
This is, I'm going to send
a message directly from one,
consumer to a producer
without a broker in the middle
to publish and subscribe.
Which is more, decoupled
then a point to point.
Point to point
isn't really that decoupled.
Publish and subscribe.
Most definitely is where
I'm publishing on a topic,
and then a subscriber is subscribing
to topics.
There's routing, and pattern
matching, out there.
There's request and reply like RPC style.
And then there's lots of other options
out there that we're doing.
The one we're going to focus on
today is primarily publish and subscribe.
Design pattern.
But let's go over each one
individually first
so that you can see kind of how it works.
Right.
So with a point to point solution,
a producer since things to a queue
and then a single consumer
is picking that up.
So the producer
is targeting a very specific,
consumer to a work queue.
It still decouples the two.
The queue access kind of that buffer
in between the two is great
for offloading, task offloading
and things, things like that.
Okay.
But point to point, that message
queue, the work
is there in in the middle
on a publish and subscribe.
The main difference here
is that the that work
queue that I had is now a generalized work
queue.
Instead it's actually a topic.
They use the word topic quite a bit.
So now I can a
producer can publish a message
on multiple top multiple topics
and those get pushed out.
And then there's a queue
for each subscriber.
So a subscriber can subscribe
to one or multiple, topics.
And there's a queue that's set up there.
So when the producer is producing things,
those messages get sent to
those queues and the subscribers
and pulling stuff off of those queues.
The great thing about this is the fan out.
I can have one producer
and millions of subscribers,
and I can have millions of producers and
one subscriber, I.
And you can do any combination of those,
it's an end to end type of,
fan out and,
architecture so that there's
a lot of benefits to that.
Routing on topics,
this one is where the message
actually carries routing keys
so it can specify
the specific topic or
in in some, some cases
this is great for like, events
and things like that.
So when an event comes in from a producer
or a message comes in from a producer,
I'm not doing it on a specific topic.
The message itself has the topic in it,
and then it'll be,
offloaded onto, onto different queues
as needed.
The benefit of this
is that the subscriber can be very fine
tuned on what events it wants or messages
it wants from the topic,
instead of it being I'm
getting all the messages on a topic.
There are some
benefits to this,
but one of the downside the benefits are,
more targeted and which means
that a subscriber is not overwhelmed
with messages it doesn't want, but it does
add a little bit of complexity.
Request and reply.
Very similar people are used
to, doing this with like, rest calls,
where a I'm sending out a request,
I get a reply back.
There are request queues and reply queues
that are in there.
This is when you really need to know
that something, you
know, was received on the other side.
And there are some benefits.
Benefits to this,
if you need that reliability.
On delivery.
But it's not as scalable.
So there's, there's your drawback, right.
Because if I'm a producer
and I'm waiting for reply, I'm
now blocked until I get that reply back.
Okay.
There are lots of different
deployment models, for these different,
design patterns and different tools.
People are moving more and more towards,
managed services
or to containerized services,
but it depends on your application
and what you're using it for.
A lot of people will just drop them
on VMs or containers
and spin them up themselves.
You get full control that way.
The other one is a managed service
where it's kind of,
outside of your infrastructure.
Maybe it's running in the cloud.
Be mindful of using cloud.
Service busses and things like that,
because your data is going in
and out of the cloud
and you could incur ingestion, and
egress costs, which is sending the data
out of the cloud.
So be mindful that,
that when you are using
a managed service
like that, that you are moving data
in and out of the cloud,
which has, cost associated with it.
The benefits of it, though, is that you
don't have to manage, these pub sub hubs
and some of them can be quite complex
so you don't get as much customization.
But the benefits
you got to look at the, the,
benefits and the costs, to see,
you know, which is best
for the program that you're working on.
High availability.
Many of these message,
brokers have, clustering capabilities,
like RabbitMQ clusters
or you have mirrored queues.
Kafka is brilliant on scaling,
for high availability and scaling.
These work very well because they share
the queues
across multiple nodes of a node goes down.
I'm not losing messages.
Most of these, queues are persistent,
which means they're stored.
So, there's lots of different options here
if you don't need a persistent queue.
They can run much faster.
Like, zoom queue is a great one for that
if you don't need persistence, or Redis
is another one that people are starting
to use as a message broker.
When you are looking inside the cloud,
make sure that you aren't
replicating your, clusters.
In the same region.
If you think you have higher availability
and you're all in the same region,
there's a danger spot
that you should be looking at.
Because if that region goes down,
which does happen at times,
then now your message,
your message queues are
down, which means every nothing
can communicate with each other.
So having geo replication is
is a good, strategy, but your costs go up,
so you gotta, you gotta
you gotta weigh the options here.
All right.
Security now
because you are moving messages across,
microservices, it's always important
to look at,
different security aspects of this.
TLS is probably the most common, of these
so that I,
I do authenticate with the broker.
So the producer authenticates
with the broker and the broker,
and the consumer authenticates.
So now,
by trust, the consumer
and producer can exchange data.
That's, that's a very, typical,
security strategy.
There's other security strategies out
there that people are starting to look at
that are role based access control.
Based or even attribute based,
working through these queues.
Remember that the queues are durable.
So you it would be great to, encrypt
the data,
in the broker because, remember,
those are, those queues can be persistent.
So you don't want that data
in the open, right?
Because if someone got access
to your broker box,
and got access to your logs or your,
queues that are persistent,
that could be an issue.
Also, make sure that you're doing
some kind of backups on those systems
if you don't have, a high
availability system, but you want to make
sure that you have those message queues,
especially if those queues grow
and the consumers have to pick things
up, you'll want to restore store
that.
Another really great thing about, these,
message brokers
is it gives you the ability to monitor,
the traffic that's going
between consumers and producers
more easily
because there's, chokepoint, chokepoint.
Right.
The broker now becomes that one place
that all that data is flowing through.
So there's lots of tools out there
that can attach to these message busses
like busses like Prometheus,
CloudWatch, Stackdriver,
these are all,
key things that can monitor,
and make
sure that you are getting the throughput
that you expect, that your producers
are doing a good job, that your consumers
are doing a good job, actually is.
It's pretty clever
way of monitoring, your,
microservice architectures.
All right.
So best practices,
make sure that as a consumer
that you are developing
into a potent, into potent, consumers.
So that if I get something
from the message bus
and I get it multiple times,
which can happen
if maybe a consumer comes down
and I have to go back and replay,
some of the cues that my behavior
doesn't change, even if I get the same
event multiple times.
Keep your messages small.
The message broker does much better with,
you know, one key messages
instead of megabyte messages,
but some of them are starting to
to go in the hundreds of KS,
type of messages.
Most of the time, if you're doing larger
than that in the megabyte range,
a lot of times people will pass a pointer
to a physical location or another.
Another means to go and grab that data
through a different port.
That's, pretty pretty typical.
To do that, make sure that you are
enforcing the schemas of the messages.
So that if a consumer makes a change
that there's
some agreement between the messages
between the consumers and the producers.
This really stinks.
If the producer is now producing
a different type of message
and none of the consumers know about it,
or even worse, if some of the consumers
know about it, but the other ones do not.
All right.
That can be, a huge, problem,
right, that you need to, handle
and then also use dead
letter cues for failures.
So if I do get a failure,
I push that into another queue.
I could have another microservice,
handle, failure.
At least I have, place
where the information is stored.
All right.
So in summary,
brokers enable scalability, reliability
and decoupled systems massively scale.
I can scale consumers and producers
independent of each other,
choose the platform in the pattern
that fits your use case best.
Not, you know, you can't use a hammer
to to put a screw in you can,
but it doesn't work very effectively.
It's the same thing
with your message broker.
Do you need a big message broker
that allows you to go to a million,
concurrent producers and consumers,
with all the complexity involved?
Or do I just need a simple zero
MQ or RabbitMQ queue
non-clustered for a simple, communication
that I'm working on,
you have to make those types of decisions
based off of your current state
of your application and use case
and your potential future state.
Using abstraction layers
between your microservices
and these message queues
is also a good way to go.
So if you have two, you could swap in
a message broker in and out very quickly.
Has your needs changed?
Or maybe even if there's a security issue,
you could easily swap out a message broker
for something more secure.