All right.
Let's talk about IaaS or infra
infrastructure as a service.
First off,
this fits really well in the cloud because
what we talk about about virtualization,
where I'm virtualizing compute,
storage, network and security
IaaS means I can do it on demand.
And this is what made cloud
really desirable to a lot of developers,
because I could easily
go to a self-service portal and say,
I need, three VMs and a network
and storage connected to them on a secure,
domain.
So that self-service part is, is critical,
for the growth of the cloud.
And I didn't have to go out and buy
machines before the cloud was long.
We saw a lot of shadow
it by people actually physically going out
and buying hardware
at like Fry's Electronics or Best Buy,
mostly Fry's in Silicon Valley,
which no longer exists.
They, you know, they're out of business.
That's an old old timers thing, I guess.
Makes me an old timer.
So I as it is that infrastructure
as a service, that ability to easily,
spin up these VMs and virtual networks
and virtual storage,
all very easily self-service portals.
Okay.
If we look at IaaS, also called software
defined infrastructure or SDI,
it has this whole concept of orchestration
where I'm orchestrating between, storage
network accelerators and compute,
all orchestrated by a software
defined orchestrator.
Right.
All resources are defined and provisioned
and managed by that orchestrator.
So there's that one point
and it makes it easy.
So there's one
API to go through in order to do this.
Or it could be a web interface
or anything like that.
Let's talk about each of the software
defined infrastructure elements.
Compute.
Compute is virtual machines
as we've already talked
about in previous lectures or vCPUs.
It also includes the Ram and everything
that's needed in there.
There's lots of public images out there
for the operating system
to run on these VMs that are available,
or you can create your own,
right.
There's also the ability to autoscale
these VMs.
I can put them in groups together
and auto scale, say I only need one VM.
Let's say it's Kafka Broker.
I only need one
VM in my cluster to begin with,
and then I can scale them
and replicate the brokers themselves,
and then they can self register
and all these cool things.
So those are auto scaling groups.
There's bare
metal provisioning that I can provision
physical servers
on demand with low latency.
And sometimes I need to do this
for licensing needs.
So software defined infrastructure
does not mean just virtual machines.
I can actually do the same thing
with bare metal provisioning.
When provisioning a bare metal box to,
to do everything that I need it to do.
And I could do it on
demand, which is pretty cool.
All right.
Storage. Let's talk about storage.
Different types of storage
that I need to worry about.
Block storage,
which is persistent disks and volumes,
tunable IOPs on this.
This is this is what we're mostly used to
when we talk about,
block storage
that's out there that most of us deal with
when at the OS level, when we're working
with that object storage.
Huge benefits,
S3 type buckets, durable blobs.
They give me Https access.
And this is what we see in the cloud
mostly as object storage.
And then I have file and NFS, storage.
There's lots in this space.
But these are network mounted file systems
that I can easily access
through the normal file system
that I'm used to.
And then there's
from your instant storage,
these are local SSDs or NVMe ease
that I use primarily for for cache.
These are running on the host themselves.
They're not out there on the network
like some of these.
Others tend to be, block storage,
object storage and file storage,
tend to be network mounted type of things.
So they're they're running more on network
infrastructure
and ephemeral, storage is local.
It is faster, primarily used for caching
and for virtual memory.
Yeah, you guessed it right.
You do not want on your
virtual memory
on us, on a software defined,
storage device. It's network bound.
That would be bad, right?
It would be slow.
And now your network bound.
All right. Networking.
Let's talk about networking.
Virtualization.
We've talked about this,
a couple in a couple other lectures.
We're isolating a, layer
three network with subnets
and routing tables
with your VPC and network virtualization.
I've got load balancers in there
that I can take advantage of.
I have a VPN where I can connect, secure
tunnels between on prem and off prem.
This will be very important
when you set up your hybrid clouds,
where you're doing
private and public clouds.
You want some VPN or direct
connect, capabilities there.
And then you have software
defined networking for routing
and netting and, and all these things
that are available as well.
And then don't forget your network
security, that you want to set up,
when you're doing this stuff.
Because security is not the responsibility
of the cloud service provider,
it's still your responsibility.
Ultimately,
they provide some tools and some,
they all have their own position
on security.
You need to understand that.
But ultimately it's your responsibility.
All right.
Security and identity.
It's it's built into every cloud service
providers.
I can't emphasize this a much and enough.
Learn
what each cloud service provider provides
and their philosophy behind,
their security understanding
that will make your, solution
much more secure.
Understanding, the different aspects,
both on identity and on security,
who's who's keeping
you know, your security tokens
and your credentials.
And are you managing them yourselves
or are they managed in the cloud?
Also, don't forget about, security
monitoring and detection.
Those are important aspects.
And like I said before,
all the cloud service providers
provide some aspects of security.
It may be sufficient for what you need.
It may not.
You need to learn what those are
and how to work in that ecosystem.
All right.
Accelerators, this is big right
now, especially with generative AI.
And talking about,
GPUs and other accelerators
that are, available out there in the cloud
service providers.
And believe it or not, many
of the instances that are in the cloud,
people don't know
that there's accelerators, baked
in, especially,
you know, a lot of the Intel instances
where they've got accelerators
baked into their CPUs.
Learn what, what instances those are
and how you can take
advantage of those accelerators
if you need speed up.
Also realize that if you are using
these accelerators, that your VMs
now need to be tied to the specific types
of accelerators that are available.
So if you are tied to like an Nvidia GPU,
you need to make sure that, VM
that you're running that the host,
the instance type
that you're running in the cloud
has that GPU available.
People tend to pay more for,
the higher end
accelerators like GPUs and FPGAs, but,
also look at the individual
CPUs because a lot of CPUs
have acceleration built in.
They're little chip
lets for no better word.
That said, directly in the CPU
that can provide, lots of acceleration
if you just know how to use it.
All right.
Some common interfaces for IaaS, a web
console.
Most of us know this.
When we go to AWS, Azure or Google,
there's a nice, web interface
or a GUI where I can easily.
Hey, I need, five instances of this,
and I need a VPN, and you're,
you know, click, click, click.
But most of the cloud service providers
provide
both a Rest API
and a command line interface or CLI,
and they also provide, software
defined, software development kits.
So from languages, I can actually start
spinning up and tearing down,
different types of,
infrastructure that I need in order to do,
my application.
There are also
and the emergence that we're going to talk
about this infrastructure as code tools
that are out there,
and there's a whole lecture on AI,
IAC, as well as, two of the most popular,
which is Terraform and Ansible.
That will, let me with code
very easily define my infrastructure,
and then it will pass
through these Yaml files or Json files
and spin up the code for me,
which is really, really kind of cool.
And then also when we talk about,
more dynamic use of Iirc
there's operation
operators and provisioner
that can do things more dynamically
based off of events that are occurring.
So, we'll, we'll cover those things,
in, in these lectures as well.
All right.
Key takeaways I want you to all understand
I has abstraction layers,
compute, storage, network
accelerators.
And don't
forget about security out there okay.
And then everything can be managed
via an API.
That's the whole idea
behind, infrastructure as a service,
that it's software defined infrastructure
that I can
with software provision, infrastructure
at will and get
whatever I need for scalability,
security and cost efficiency.