Okay.
Let's talk about container orchestration.
Specifically.
Let's talk about Docker Swarm, which as we
mentioned in previous lectures.
Docker swarm is a built in
orchestrator engine for Docker.
And with the philosophy
behind it to be simple.
All right.
So it's highly opinionated, which means
that it sets things up a certain way
and very little configuration
very little options there.
Unlike Kubernetes
has a lot of different options.
Docker swarm the idea is to make it simple
to have your Docker,
compose file actually run, services
across a set of machines
instead of a single machine.
So that's the idea behind it.
This is great
if you're developing something and,
you're the developer and just focusing on
maybe running things, very quickly,
or if you have an environment
that's, pretty simple, straightforward,
production environment
that you don't need.
Really complicated.
Networking or storage
or anything like that, that Kubernetes
gives you more complex configurations.
So let's take a look at some of the key
concepts here.
First off, the concept instead of
a Kubernetes cluster, we've got a swarm.
Right.
And a swarm is one or more Docker hosts
that are acting
like a single virtual Docker engine.
They're acting like it,
but they don't necessarily behave like it.
Right.
So inside your swarm, you're
going to have nodes inside your swarm,
and the nodes take on different personas,
whether it's a manager node
where it's scheduling
tasks and maintain state,
or a worker node
which is actually running the containers.
Right.
So you've got those two types of nodes
that are out there and the individual
service is
what's
the best way to define it's an end point.
So in the it's an endpoint in the whole
ecosystem that you've established,
it can be served up by multiple
containers of the same type
or one container.
And the the key thing here is that it
defines,
the certain number of replicas
that I can do there
or networks and configurations and secrets
are all contained inside that service.
So if I have replicas, set up,
it will give me continuity
and reliability, even if I have one
replica set up and it fails,
it will kick off automatically.
Again, a new container.
So it handles all that container
orchestration for that specific service.
Then you have individual task.
This is a single container instance
that's running part of a service.
I can
have multiple
tasks running in an individual service.
There's startup tasks
and then there's running tasks
and even shutdown tasks that you can see
that are individual containers
that are running.
Then the next one, probably one of
the most powerful things, is a stack.
And a stack
is made up of a set of services,
or collection of services that are defined
in your Docker compose file.
So I can do a Docker stack deploy
pass in a docker compose file,
and it will instantiate
all those services for me
and have all the can in
containers starting up and running
and everything I need it to do.
It's super cool, very, very cool stuff.
We talked in previous
about different network.
Options and you can use different
networks, in your Docker compose,
overlay networks
are what are primarily used,
but you can also attach to networks.
So I can have two Docker stacks
running from two different Docker
compose files that can actually talk
to each other through a common network
that you can define, either
outside of the,
the docker compose,
or you can define it inside the docker
compose and make it attachable so
someone else can actually use it as well.
So let's talk
let's start talking about Docker
Compose and or Docker Swarm
and how to get things started.
The first thing you need to do
is initialize Docker swarm.
Then you need to add nodes to it.
And then you need to verify those nodes.
The verification of the nodes
is important for security.
If you before when they didn't
have verification of nodes, nodes
could just automatically come in and,
you didn't know who's in your swarm.
This you're passing token keys.
So now they're sharing keys
between each other and it guarantees
more secure, environment.
Okay.
So first we do a Docker swarm init
and we can,
you can just do a Docker
swarm init and you're done
absolute.
Or if you have multiple, nic cards
or multiple
networks already established on the host,
you can specify which subnet you're going
to, advertise on, which will be the subnet
that the management,
network that's going to be used
for this Docker swarm.
People that set up
large systems tend to have 2 or 3 hard
physical networks in their boxes,
and they use one of those like an admin,
network.
They'll use those that subnet
to, to do the advertising.
Okay.
Now then when you get on each individual
node in your swarm
to join the swarm,
you just type in swarm join
and then the token which is the worker
token that was printed out
when you did the Docker init,
they'll give you a token name.
And so you give that token.
And then you give the IP
address of the manager.
And then the port 2377,
you can run into problems
if you're using ubuntu
and it's locked down all the ports.
You need to make sure that you establish
that I need 2377 open
so I can communicate
between, the different hosts,
remember, that for,
for the networking, privileges
and things like that.
Make sure that you do open up those ports
and that these hosts
can actually talk to each other.
They don't have to be on the same subnet,
but they have to be able to,
at least get to the other
subnet of the manager nodes.
You can list all the nodes inside
your swarm with Docker node
ls very common, command
that you should be used to
if you already using Linux,
that ls command for list.
Okay, now that we've got our Docker
swarm initialized and set up
and I've added nodes, let's take a look
at deploying individual services.
Now you can create an individual service
with Docker service create
or you can put in a stack
that has services in it.
We're going to show
first how to do it
outside of a Docker compose file.
And then we'll look at how that runs
inside a docker, compose file.
But anything you do in a Docker
compose file, you can actually do
on the command line as well.
So really quickly to create a service
docker service create
you can give it a name.
You can say how many replicas
you want running.
You can talk about the ports,
the published ports.
The published 80 target is 80.
And you can give the image name
like in this case it's
nginx and I'm grabbing
the latest off of engine X.
Remember
not always wise to always grab latest
because it could change out
from underneath you,
especially if you're hitting a repository
that's a public repo like Docker Hub.
They make updates all the time.
Now you may not care.
You may say, hey,
I actually want the latest all the time,
but that is can get really difficult
for repeatability in your CI
CD pipeline, so be careful about that.
Okay,
now I can also update a service,
which is really, really cool
that I can update a running service
and I can do that.
I can even update the image
that it's, using.
I can do delays.
I can say update.
How many of the replicas
am I going to update concurrently?
If we already have a started service
like we did for web,
where I had three replicas,
I could do update parallelism at three,
but then I'm going to lose
some of my reliability
on that nginx web server,
so it's best to do it one at a time.
What's going to happen
is as one of those tasks
that are running under the service,
which is one of those replicas
of the container,
as it updates as soon as it's back up
into a running state,
then it'll go and do the next one
and next one, and the traffic coming in
will be hitting the service,
which is a gateway,
and it's a round robin of load balancer.
It it will round
robin the requests through those services
as they're,
as they're in the proper states,
which is really cool.
All right.
So I can update running, services.
This way.
Okay.
I can also look and see what's going on
with certain services
and the tasks that have run and are
currently running with the command.
So Docker service PS and then web,
that will give me all the processes
that have run on, on web across
all the machines that it's running on.
Which is very different than Docker PS.
Docker PS will only show me the containers
that are running on the current host
docker service.
PS and then the
the service name will show me
all of the, tasks
that are running for that service
across the swarm,
which is super cool.
I can also change the scale of my web
by giving just a scale command,
and I can say, hey, I need to scale this
service up to five replicas.
Service scale the web,
which is the, can service name.
And then I say, hey,
equal to five and boom, all of a sudden
I have five replicas running. Now,
which is super cool.
That's all from the command line.
All right, so that's individual services.
Let's talk about stacks.
Remember
a stack is a collection of services
that are running together
probably on the same set of networks.
And most of the time,
you have them on the same network,
but you can even segment inside a stack.
Multiple networks,
and you can have bridges
between the networks and all that stuff.
But the idea of a stack is it's one,
package, a collection of services
that I can control
and manage from one point,
using Docker stack commands.
So the first thing I want to do
is create a Docker compose file.
In this case here
I only have one service called app.
But that's okay
I, I the key elements are here.
I can have multiple services.
I can have app and web and database.
I can specify how many replicas they have.
I can specify the update
configs, the ports that I need publish to,
and then even networks in this case
here of this Docker compose file.
And there's lots of examples,
that are available out there.
So you can see how a lot of these are run
in this example
here I have an overlay network
which if you remember
that's a a VCs.
So it is creating a subnet out there
that all of the
services that are on the same network,
the ASP.Net network.
And in this case there's just one.
But if I had, you know, multiple services
defined in my Docker compose,
then they would
all connect to that network
and they could all access each other
through the service name,
which is that gateway.
So you don't access individual replicas.
Instead you access the service
through its name.
You can also set up, aliases to,
those services as well,
which is actually pretty slick.
I can set up different, aliases.
Okay.
If I want to deploy this stack,
it's really simple.
Docker
stack, deploy pass in the compose file
and then name your stack.
In this case I named it my stack.
And I'm using that docker compose file
that I just showed you.
So when I do this when I say docker stack
deploy
it's going to run a docker
run or Docker service create for each
one of those services, which in turn
runs a docker run on the back end.
With everything configured,
all the networks set up properly.
If I have volumes defined in the service,
it will define.
It will create those volumes and attach
all those replicas
to those, to that volume
that it established.
Super cool.
It handles a lot of the hard work for you
when you're thinking
about multiple containers
that are talking to each other,
our services
and all the different replicas
that are running in those services,
it handles all the management for you,
which is really, really nice.
Okay, I can manage the stack as well.
I can list all the stacks again.
Docker stack ls for list.
I can, look at all of my services
running in my stack
by saying Docker stack services,
and then the stack name.
I can look at all of the containers
that are running in my stack
by doing a stack and the stack name,
and then I can blow away the stack,
by doing a remove,
this will shut down all the containers
and clean up, the networks and volumes.
Anything else that it created for
that stack was really nice and simple.
Remember I mentioned before
Docker, their philosophy is,
one button install, one button use,
and they've done it.
They've done a great job with this. Here.
Let's talk about the networking
a little bit.
I inferred it a little bit.
There's that overlay network.
Now if I were to do it by hand,
from the command line I would
do docker network create D for
and then overlay network
and then I gave it.
Net or I can use the
do it in Docker compose.
Have you as you saw in the earlier
example, if I want to attach a service
to a network, I use the dash dash
network flag in this case it would be app.
Net is what I'm attaching to right
by and attaching to networks.
In other stacks is available as well
because you create this app.
Net network
and you say, hey, this is attachable.
So it will create in in a namespace
that you can attach to
so that allows you to attach
different stacks together.
So that they can communicate.
Now here's here's the killer about this
though they may be on the same subnet
and the
same network, but you need to make sure
that you're going through the proper,
gateways, to get all that stuff done.
So if you have multiple networks,
set them up appropriately.
Make sure that all your services
that you need to talk to each other
on the same network,
I've seen time and time again
where people have forgotten
to add a certain service onto a network,
and they were trying to connect it
from another stack, and they didn't
have the service that they were trying to,
directly connect to there.
So that can be problematic sometimes.
Also, we've got ingress, into the stack,
and this can happen through,
an entry point where the stack is running.
And remember,
that typically has to be a manager node,
but not necessarily has to be not
necessarily is a manager node.
If I'm trying to access from the outside.
Okay.
Configs and secrets.
Another really important aspect of swarms.
Because you do have these tokens
and certifications that,
you want to make sure
that your services have
and that they can share with each other.
So in order to do that,
the best thing to do is to create a secret
and attach that those secrets to a service
or a stack.
Right.
And you can reference those in compose,
or you can use a configuration file.
So in this case maybe I've got a password.
I'm going to create the password
into a secret vault.
In this case my DB password is going into
my create,
my secret vault that I have here.
So I'm creating a DB password.
In this case, it's called DB password.
Surprise, surprise.
Okay, now, if I want
to use those secrets in my docker compose,
I can specify secrets,
and I can specify which secret
I'm I'm using for passwords or whatever
the case may be.
So you can see here
I've declared which secret I'm using.
I'm saying that it's external
because it's an external,
secret vault,
not just contained inside the stack.
And I'm actually using it
in the DB service here.
Okay.
I can also, create a config
where I've got different configurations
that I'm using, and then I can pass
into these stacks as well.
Okay.
Another really interesting thing
that you should do for Docker Swarm
if you need high availability
and fault tolerance.
The managers that I have running in swarm,
if you just have one manager
and that no goes down, you're dead.
You're toast.
Right.
Because the manager's the one that's
coordinating and orchestrating everything.
So it's best to run these
if you need high availability
in, 3 or 5 to form a quorum.
Odd numbers are the best way
because it uses raft consensus to do this.
Make sure you have enough worker nodes.
Your manager nodes
can act as worker nodes as well.
If you have a small configuration,
maybe you only have five nodes.
You want to use those worker
nodes, as well.
Or you want to use those manage
your nodes as well.
It's kind of lame to have three manager
nodes and two worker nodes.
In fact, by default
you guessed it, Docker Swarm uses
the manager nodes by default,
which is really kind of nice.
Also realize that,
your deployment strategies
that you have make sure that you're
automatically well, and by default
it automatically keeps trying to run
failed task over and over again
on different nodes.
It'll rotate it through.
Now this is really interesting
and you need to watch for this
when you're debugging a stack.
If you've got a,
image that is not properly configured
or something like that and tries
to start a container and it fails,
it'll keep failing
over and over and over again,
and you'll be sitting there going,
I wonder what's going on.
It's not working.
Well, take a look at your logs to,
do a stack, logs.
And you can look at your logs
across all the services.
Or you can pick one service specifically
and look at its logs.
It'll give you the logs
of all the tasks that have run,
which can be very beneficial.
You can see what's going on.
Okay.
Best practices I already mentioned some of
this three manager nodes for resiliency.
Label your nodes.
Because if you have a special node
let's say it's
a high end server,
that you're using for database.
And you want to make sure
that your containers always land on that
cluster of, database, servers.
You can actually,
when you, configure a node
or you can update a node,
by giving it a role.
And, that's, that could be beneficial
because now you can target that
in your Docker compose saying, hey,
I need this to run on this kind of node.
Which could be, very, very useful.
Also, use some health checks
in your compose to enable
starting and rescheduling.
Take a look at, at health
checks in the Docker compose,
configuration guides and documentation
also limit the service update parallelism.
If you update the whole thing,
you can get a, degradation in service
while you're doing an update.
If you if you or you get total downtime
while it's updating everything.
In some cases you want to do that because
you don't want anything new coming in.
In other cases, you want to do rolling.
Use that parallelism to help you do that,
and then rotate your secrets
via, version secret updates and service
updates.
Right.
It's great
that you've got secrets and tokens,
but if you're not rotating them,
someone could be in there
and you wouldn't even know it.
So, watch out for that.
All right, as I already mentioned
before, Docker Swarm, it goes towards,
opinionated over
or convention over configurability.
And because of that, it's easy
to set up and easy to use.
It really is ideal for small, medium
deployments if I'm doing a massive
deployment across hundreds of nodes,
probably not what you want to go with.
You want to go with something
more like Kubernetes,
but realize that Kubernetes
is more complex.
And, most of the time your Docker
compose can run on Kubernetes
as well as Docker Swarm.
So if you're a developer,
I always stick with Docker Swarm.
It's much easier to manage and handle,
and then I can deploy those Docker
compose files out to, Kubernetes cluster.
Pretty straightforward.