One of the key elements of IaaS
or infrastructure as a service,
is the ability to quickly and program
programmability.
Launch, whole infrastructure
of compute, storage,
network security and accelerators.
One of the key elements of
that is infrastructure as code.
So I want to go over the key
elements of infrastructures code.
And then we'll talk about
in other lectures
about, different tools
that enable infrastructures
code like Ansible and Terraform.
Right.
So the idea here is that we can treat
infrastructure as versioned code.
This is really important
if you want, continuous
deployment
and, reliability on your deployment.
And the ability to scale
is very important with this too.
So what it means now is that a software
developer can put in conjunction with,
their sysadmin,
they can work together to say
this piece of code or this microservice
or this application
requires this infrastructure,
and it can be checked in together
into GitHub or into subversion or heaven
forbid, people are so using clear case.
But I was a clear case.
I have been for years.
You should look that up
if you don't know what it is.
Very cool system,
but that I can check this all in together.
So the application, the infrastructure,
everything is version together.
This allows me
to do automatic provisioning,
configuration and tear down very easily.
It gives me that repeatability
and consistency
that I need
in these highly complex systems,
because there's nothing worse in the world
than deploying your system
and finding out,
oh, someone forgot they didn't follow
the install the structure instructions.
They forgot to flip this one little bit
in order to make everything work.
Infrastructure's code
gives me that capability
of defining everything,
and I can version control it as well.
Together.
So why it matters
safe reruns and produce the same state
that into potency is extremely important.
The version controls we talked about,
I can look and see
what the differences are between version
two and version one.
Both of the application code
and the infrastructure it's running on.
Right.
And then I can also share very easily.
This infrastructure is code.
I can share this
between different projects very easily
if I have a standard way
of doing things that includes auditability
and security aspects.
Those can all fit into these,
modules or cookbooks or blue books.
There's lots of different names for them
that I can use over and over again
for, different,
projects.
I can also inject these into my CI
CD pipeline,
my continuous integration and continuous
deployment pipelines for rapid deployment.
And it serves as a way of documenting what
the infrastructure requirements are for,
you guessed it, your applications.
All right.
Let's talk about the different,
declarative and imperative, Iirc.
So declarative says describe
what the final state should be.
And the tool figures out
how to get to that final state.
Examples of this are Terraform
cloud formation arm bicep saltstack.
There's lots of them out there. Right?
Imperatives says
here are the step by step commands.
It need to run.
So one is declarative.
This is what the end state
should look like.
And the other one is take these steps.
Ansible, chef and puppet are the step
by step run this command and this command
and this command.
Right.
You have greater control
over the execution flow in imperative
but declarative.
Make sure
that you get to a specific end state.
So we're going to talk
we're going to talk in these lectures
about Ansible which is imperative.
And Terraform which is declarative.
So you get to see both.
All right.
There's different categories
of these tools we're going to go over.
There's like five of these categories
real quickly provisionals.
These are
the things that are actually provisioning,
taking the éac
and actually doing the provisioning,
setting up the machines, the networks,
the storage
and configuring all that stuff.
Okay.
That's what a provisioner is.
Configuration management.
They're installing software,
configuring OS services and,
on servers and things like that.
So they're not just
provisioning the hardware.
There are also installing software
and things like that.
Okay.
Then there's orchestrating and templating.
These are for multi-tiered application.
And templates
examples of these are cloud formations.
Azure.
Google the deployment manager.
The cool thing about this is I can set up
not just individual machines,
but now I'm setting up
lots of machines.
Right. Multi-tiered architectures.
So I've got maybe a lamp stack
or I've got, a three tiered architecture,
or maybe I'm doing a message broker,
with consumers and producers
and things like that.
That orchestrator
and template is important there.
And then we've got containerization and
containers and Kubernetes and operators.
They're managing the infrastructure via,
Kubernetes, creds and controllers.
And examples of this are helm
charts, flux, Argo CD,
Terraform operators, things like that.
All right.
Here are some of the most popular AI tools
that are out there.
We are going to in the lectures
cover Terraform in Ansible.
Terraform came from HashiCorp.
It's got a declarative SQL, language.
They call it the HashiCorp
configuration language.
It has multi-cloud support
and a large, very large, community.
So there's a lot of tools
I can just lift and start using.
Plumie is an interesting one
in that I can do code first
so I can use, the language.
Maybe I'm writing stuff in JavaScript
or Python.
My application,
I can use that same, language,
to now do infrastructure, coding as well.
Ansible is agent lists.
It uses Yaml as its primary, playbook.
And it's to, in its imperative.
And so I'm telling it, the individual
steps that I want it to make.
Right.
Chef and puppet are Ruby based.
Which is a language
if you don't know Ruby.
It's a pretty cool language.
But Ruby base
that is declaring the desired states,
configuration, cloud
formation is another great one.
It's native to AWS,
but it will run on Azure and G and GCP.
And it can detect, drift detection.
As, as I'm deploying things,
which is nice.
And then cross plane is a Kubernetes
native
control plane
for provisioning cloud resources.
All right.
I act workflow real quickly. Very simple.
It's it should be very similar
to your software.
Define your software
development. Workflow.
I write the code I stored in git.
I do peer reviews, I execute a plan,
which is basically,
running the running the code
and it will go out
and, do the provisioning
and then I can apply it, the changes
that I need to make
and it will make updates
to my infrastructure,
and then I can monitor any drift
that I have and reapply code as I need to.
And then don't forget the last step.
Make sure you destroy resources
when they're no longer needed,
especially in the public cloud,
as you'll be paying for those resources.
All right, key takeaways IAC shifts
infrastructure from manually doing it in
or even via the,
the web interface to choosing
to doing it more automatic and repeatable.
You need to choose whether you're
going to use a declarative or imperative,
tool.
And that should be based off
the use case that you have.
If you need high control over
configuration,
then you'll want to do more imperative
than declarative, right?
If you want something,
where you want to know what the in state
is quickly without a lot of steps,
declarative is a better way to go.
Make sure that you are leveraging,
version control, just like you would do
with your software,
and include it into your CI, CD pipeline.
It will make your life so much easier
when you go off and, start,
scaling this to the massive,
massive, startup that you're going
to start make billions of dollars with,
make sure that you are selecting a tool
that handles multi-cloud
so that you have that ability
to, move between cloud service providers
and even move back to on prem
with private cloud is you need to.