All right,
let's talk about, container networking.
And this is not the end all, end
all lectures on container tech, right?
This is just a primer.
And there's a lot to cover in
in this on the different types of networks
and what that means when you're deploying
and understanding them, is very important
when you're trying
to create these ecosystem of microservices
that talk to each other.
So let's dive right in.
So the first are the basic building blocks
that are created.
So if I look at the basic building blocks
every container
gets its own network
namespace individual container.
By default
it gets its own networking, namespace.
It means it has isolated
interfaces, routes, firewalls, rules.
Everything is in
for that individual container.
They're managed via IP, a net, and s
or automatically
by the individual, orchestrators.
Right?
So it's important to understand,
if I have a container running,
that, Ethernet zero f eth0
is the, on container A,
and I can have any eth0 on container B
when it, maps into the individual host,
they have their own virtual, interface
there that are uniquely named.
But in the container themselves,
they can have the same names
because they have their own own namespace.
Right?
They're completely isolated.
One of the reasons they did this
is because I can define in an image
very easily,
the same exact.
I can have the same exact image
running in a, in multiple containers,
and they're all going to have
the same network interface.
I'm going to have all that, which means
as a developer, it's much easier for me.
I don't have to write special code
to handle.
What is the the networking, card
that's on here?
All that,
all that's taken care of for you.
And it's the same everywhere,
but because it's the same everywhere,
it means that there's some back end things
that have to happen right in order
to talk to these containers,
because they're all listening
on their own virtual, Ethernet,
port their or their,
their own virtual network,
I should say not Ethernet port.
All right. Let's take a look.
So if I look real closely at this,
I've got these virtual Ethernet pairs.
One is running on the host
and one is running
on the in the container itself. Right.
So one end of the container namespaces.
You know, network eth0.
That's the network card.
And the other one will be on virtual
Ethernet,
ABC 123 XYZ, whatever it is.
Right.
When packets are sent to one end, they're
automatically sent to the other end.
They appear at the other end
automatically.
Right.
So that's important to understand
that distinction.
When it comes in on one end,
it automatically hits the other end okay.
All right.
So let's take a look at that concept with
something called a Linux bridge.
So with the Linux bridge it's a host
level bridge that bridges between
the Docker container and the host.
Remember that virtual interface
that I have there
that is going to be mapped to the eth0
in the container.
Right.
So what it means is
the host can connect to multiple,
of these, virtual Ethernet
and so that means that I can have the host
now connect to multiple containers
through the different virtual Ethernet.
Interfaces.
Okay.
It acts kind of like a virtual switch.
It learns with, the virtual Mac addresses.
And forwards to the individual ports
that I've specified on, on the bridge.
Now, here's here's
where things get a little tricky.
If I have the same,
port mapping to multiple containers,
I can't do that.
Right.
Because the switch won't know
which one to get to go to.
And in the default Linux bridge,
in this case, it won't round robin
or anything like that.
It'll actually give you an error.
So if I have on the Linux bridge,
I say port
88 is going to map to, all the containers.
That won't work.
I have to map to individual, containers.
So I may have an 8080
that maps to container one 8080.
I may have an 8081 maps to container
two, port 8080
or a third one 8082
mapping to port 8080 on a third container.
Right.
I can't assign all those containers
to the same one in a Linux bridge.
Okay.
That's important to understand.
Well, there are some techniques
I know you're saying,
but Darren,
I know, I know, I've done this before.
There are some techniques with different
networking techniques that can do that.
But the Linux bridge, that's
that's the most simplest way to do things.
That's what it means.
Okay. So,
this is like I've already mentioned,
this is the most common
and it's the default, Docker network
is the bridge, which as I mentioned
before, traffic goes from the container
to the virtual interface to the bridge to,
a virtual interface
and to another container.
If I want to connect two containers
together, the host actually uses a Nat
for external, access, to access,
that, virtual bridge
that I have sitting there.
Right.
So even though, Docker containers
that are attached to the host bridge
will share the same subnet,
they're still going through the bridge
to communicate with each other, right.
Because the host
has has all those mappings in there.
And what to do.
Okay.
Let's take a look at some of the,
different modes that are out there.
Right. A default Docker bridge.
There's a great plant
UML diagram in the lecture notes.
It's so big.
I didn't want to put it on here
because it would be too small.
But take a look at it. In the lecture
notes.
The idea here again is that the containers
are, attached to the host bridge.
By default,
all the containers share the same subnet.
And that all that communication is going
through that bridge
from one container to another.
And anyone that's accessing from
the outside is accessing through,
a Nat on that host.
Okay.
Let's look at the host networking.
So containers share the,
share a host network namespace.
There's no isolation
if I'm using host networking.
Now, we mentioned in another lecture
that in only on Linux
can I do host networking.
So what this means here
is that the container
is not isolated
from all the traffic coming into the host,
and it maps to a specific host interface,
and it's shared with the host itself.
So if it's eth0
it's going to be F0 on on the host.
Right.
There is no isolation here
and it defeats some of the purpose,
but it could be for high performance
and low isolation.
So again this only works on Linux hosts
that are doing this okay.
You can use these.
But remember
you lose some of the isolation, but
you decrease the amount of latency
and increase some of the throughput
that can happen in these cases.
Okay.
If I don't specify,
a network, if I say none,
the container has its own namespace,
but no interfaces,
which means you're right,
it can't talk to anything else.
Right? Nothing can talk to it.
It's use.
It's useful for some specialized
networking setup, type things
where I don't want
any anyone. Accessing it.
And it only can access the loopback,
mechanism that's in there.
So these are good for specific things
where you don't want network.
Specifically.
All right.
Then there's a concept of a mac,
Vlan and IPV LAN.
So this is where I directly attach
the containers virtual interface
to a physical Nic running on the device.
So if I do this, then I can pin
certain containers to certain network
cards, sitting or network interfaces
sitting inside on the host machine.
So that attaches to that physical Nic.
This is great
if I need to really fine tune,
containers so that,
they're using the best networking
for what they need it for.
So if I have some admin
type of containers,
I'll use an admin Nic that's
maybe only a one gig,
network interface, but if I have some,
containers
that I need to tie to my 100 gig.
Nic, because I it's consuming
a lot of data and spitting data out,
or I've got several of those.
I want to tie
those to those specific, NICs.
So that gives me that ability to,
tie those to specific NICs.
Okay.
All right.
This is all on one machine so far.
But how good is that?
Unless I have a machine
that's got, you know, 12,000 cores
and, 20PB of memory
and, you know, exabytes of data
sitting all on one machine.
That is not very useful, right?
I really want to run on multiple host.
Well, this is where things
get really interesting.
And one of the networks I like to use
the most is an overlay network,
which is a micro segmented network
that can connect, connect
multiple machines
all on different subnets.
They can be on the same subnet
or different subnets.
But this overlay network
can actually create
an overlay subnet on top of an underlying
network topology.
So it's independent of the network
topology that's there.
So the way that this works is again
we still have that virtual Ethernet
interface on container A
and container B in this case.
But in this case
they're running on different host.
And then instead of it going to the bridge
it's going to go to an overlay network.
And the overlay network
can span multiple hosts.
And then create a Vlan tunnel right.
That connects those hosts
into its own network.
Right.
So on each one of these host,
I got to run a network agent, right.
With Docker
Swarm it's running a Docker swarm agent.
There's flannel, there's weave.
There's calico.
To manage
those tunnels between the different host
and these tunnels create their own,
subnet that's running on top of,
the network
that's already established there.
So this gives me isolation so I can have
two containers on two different hosts
that are on two different subnets,
look like they're on the same subnet,
have the same, firewall rules
for that, subnet.
It's very powerful tool.
And there's other ones out there.
There's other
what's this Vlan or Vxlan
type of, overlay networks
that are more high, secure
or higher speed.
There's, more highly configurable.
There's different options for this.
This is where Kubernetes really shines
because they give you the ability
to plug in different, overlay network,
controllers and things like that,
where with Docker Swarm, Docker
Swarm picks one and goes with it.
Right.
So if I don't really care about,
configuring a network
because I've got the standard
one is just fine for me.
Docker swarm is a good way to go
if I do care about maybe higher
security,
higher scalability, things like that.
Then I will want to
I will want to work with,
a different network controller.
Important here that the hosts appear
on the same L2 network.
Like I said, the same the same subnetwork.
Okay.
There's, different flavors.
So here is a BGP, routing based, calico.
So this is calico. How calico works.
It uses
BGP routing instead of encapsulation.
So each host programs
the Linux routing tables.
For the container subnets.
So that's kind of the calico.
Way to go.
The advantages here is there's no overhead
like I have in the other ones where
there is overhead where they're doing
the mappings dynamically.
This is more,
happening at the L3 native L3, routing.
So I don't have some of the overhead,
on speed
between, these calico is an easy,
plug in with, Kubernetes.
So, in fact, I can't remember.
Kubernetes does this, natively out of the
that if that's their default or not.
But I know that it's use
with a lot of success
in, Kubernetes, ecosystem.
Okay.
Another interesting thing is people
have started looking at instead of layer
two, layer
three in the network on the same subnets,
they're moving all the way up to layer
seven, the application layer,
for a overlay network.
So instead of eating concerning yourself
with subnets, they're going to directly to
this idea of connecting by name.
Right.
And a great example of this is it's
you or link or D does this sort of thing,
which means that the containers
talk to each other by name and,
it can provide a quite, a quite
a bit of really interesting concepts
like load balancing can be built
into this, encryption,
TLS encryption at the application layer
instead of at the network layer.
So moves everything up to that
higher layer.
Some of the downsides of service meshes,
especially in, edge computing
when you're in multi-cloud
or hybrid cloud computing is,
these tend
to be very chatty on the network
because you're constantly checking
to see, where services are.
All right.
So, be a little bit mindful
if you're doing some hybrid stuff,
whether you want to do
an echo service mesh or not.
Because there is a lot of chatty overhead
that goes on on between them.
Right?
Especially if you're working in contested
environments on the edge.
And you
don't have that full network connectivity
all the time, it's
you, can actually isolate services
that are still running.
If there's hiccups in the network because
they all say it doesn't exist anymore.
So be mindful of that.
Also, they use a sidecar proxy,
which is really interesting.
For the individual service, it's
almost like this little sidecar
that's sitting there
that's handling all the network traffic
in and out of the sidecars and sidecars
as well, are really talking to each other.
All right.
So let's talk about the container network
interface.
In Kubernetes
it's a pluggable standard for Kubernetes
and other orchestrators.
Like I said Mesos had it.
And I do believe Nomad has it as well.
There's very popular CNN plug ins
or CNI plug ins, calico,
which is the BGP routing.
Remember,
that's changing the routing tables
on the individual machines, flannel,
which is creating
a full blown Vxlan, overlay network.
There's a weave net,
which is a mesh overlay,
which we've talked about that as well.
Right.
A service mesh, psyllium, and bridge,
which we're all familiar with.
Bridge.
So the CNN configuration,
you're going to see these,
being defined for Kubernetes, primarily
Docker just uses bridge and Docker Swarm,
uses a vxlan overlay, concept.
All right.
So here is a, sequence diagram
that shows how a Kubernetes
orchestrator is going to, set
everything up.
So it's first going to read the different,
CNN plugins that are available
and their configurations.
It's going to create,
a network namespace.
It's going to create the
the virtual Ethernet pairs
that are required
right between the container and the host.
And then it's going to configure all the,
IP and routes that it needs to,
and it's going to attach the host
to a bridge or an overlay network.
And then we're off of off and running.
Right.
And that is
and then I've got tear down too,
that I need to do that's described there.
So that gives you kind of an idea
of everything that has to happen
to set all this stuff up.
All right.
So the next thing we
we kind of touched on this a little bit
with the mesh networks, but the,
the bridge networks, the overlay networks
and the BGP networks
also have the, service discovery,
because it doesn't
do me any good to hardcode
IP paths in the images.
That just doesn't work.
Right.
I need to that to be more dynamic. So,
all of these network techniques
use a DNS domain name service.
So in my docker compose or helm
charts, whatever I'm using, I can specify,
two services
that need to talk to each other.
And the DNS will know
when that container comes up.
It registers with the DNS
and says I am this container.
This is my host hostname.
Right.
So now I can access these containers
by a hostname which is really important
when you're orchestrating
multiple containers.
And you need them to talk to each other
and share information with each other.
Right.
Just like I mentioned before it, Docker
Swarm
chooses a specific methodology to use it.
Does DNS,
internally it's got an embedded DNS
where Kubernetes lets me,
plug in my own different ones.
Either core DNS or kube DNS, and
there's others I can plug into it as well.
Right.
So that's important to understand.
Kubernetes more configurable Docker swarm.
It is
much more what's the right word.
It's already configured.
It's opinionated.
That's the word I'm looking for.
It's highly opinionated.
So it chooses a way.
And you work in that way
or you don't write,
or you go to Kubernetes
where you can choose whatever you want.
All right.
Security,
and network
policies are really important by default.
Docker containers, have no ports open.
So you have to actually do the mappings
yourself, right.
Like, you notice on the Docker line,
I can say dash p and say which ports
I want mapped from the host to the,
individual, container port.
Right. That's on an individual host.
When I'm
talking about a Docker swarm
or a Kubernetes cluster.
Now, I have firewall rules
that I need to establish in there as well.
And that's important to understand
what the each one
brings to the table
and how to configure those.
A lot of times I've spent,
I can't tell you how many hours
making sure I have the right ports set up.
I said these
should be talking to each other,
but they're not talking to each other.
So making sure that you have those,
and understand
those appropriately is important.
Okay.
Best practices,
single host
development environments, bridge simple.
Easy, easy to use.
Right.
If you want the container
talking to the host network,
use that host, if you need to.
A lot of times you really don't want
a container talking to the host machine.
If you're doing that,
you're doing something wrong.
You should probably have another container
that does that work, for you.
Right.
Leverage network policies,
in cilium, for the least privileged
communications, of course, across,
Kubernetes, cluster,
if you're using that Docker
Swarm by default, kind of set
that up as pretty locked locked down.
Right.
Make sure you're monitoring
your network performance.
Especially with lands.
They can they can get, slow at times.
And making sure
that you've established those, correctly.
And then most importantly,
document your network design.
Don't just leave it up
to to chance, right.
Understand
how things are connected together.
You will spend a lot of time
working through your network, topologies.
If you haven't written down, and designed
and organized, you'll do far better
when you're trying to debug, microservices
talking to each other.
All right.
Go out there and learn more about, Linux,
Linux container networking.
Understand
just the core fundamentals of it.
And that will help you so much further
along when you start looking at,
deploying your own microservice
architectures
and the networking options
that you have there, remember that,
running on a single host is a lot easier
than running on a cluster of machines.
Understanding those different network
topologies and different network
techniques, can be, very important
as you move forward.
Take a look at service meshes.
There's a lot to
there's a lot of benefits to them,
with security controls and routing
and things at the application layer,
but also understand the downsides
to service meshes
and compare and contrast
between the different network types.