All right, here's
just a primer on container orchestration.
I'm not going to go over the details of
every different container orchestration,
but some common terms that you should know
about container orchestration
and why we have it and and its importance.
So first off, the purpose of orchestration
as I create start
creating these microservice architectures
where I have instead of one big
VM or even four VMs for that matter,
I, I change that to now
I have several dozen microservices.
Well, I've got to be able to orchestrate
and make sure that these,
microservices are spinning up
and tearing down at the right times.
That's one of the beauties of containers.
The time to spin up and tear down is so
small, it's in milliseconds or second,
very few seconds.
Right.
That I want to not consume resources
I don't need.
So there's a lot of,
spinning up and tearing down and
connecting these microservices together.
So I need an automated way of scheduling
and placing these, containers
on the right machines, with the right
configurations that that I need out there.
So that's why one of the main reasons
why we need orchestration.
Right?
Also, the benefit of microservices is
if a microservice goes down
for some reason,
I don't have to completely fail
the whole system.
So there's self-healing and failover
that I need.
I also gives me an opportunity
to do rolling, updates.
So I have no downtime or very little
downtime as I'm making code changes.
This fits into that, continuous delivery,
a methodology
that's kind of been developed
over the last 10 or 15 years.
Now, another thing that's important here
is I have microservices, and
they need to share data with each other,
and they need to talk to each other,
either through a message bus
or directly to each other's
lots of different protocols out there.
They need to be able
to discover each other,
and that's really important.
Otherwise I can't get any work done.
So that's that's another key element
that I need to understand.
And then I also want to be able to load
balance
as, I can handle more and more loads.
I want to make sure that I'm hitting all
the microservices that I have out there.
So that's
what the orchestrator is responsible for,
right?
It's all that stuff that a lot of times
in microservice
architectures, we end up, oh,
I gotta write that myself or whatever.
The beauty of container orchestration,
a lot of that heavy lifting that you would
normally have to do
is done for you in the orchestrators,
which is really, really cool, right?
Again, remember the whole,
container ecosystem starting with Docker.
Their whole point was make it easy.
That's the whole point.
Make it easy, easy to use.
Our goal was to help developers
focus on not the infrastructure,
but focus on the algorithms
and the code that they need to write.
So that's one of one of the key things.
So managing all that complexity
of deploying microservices,
managing them is extremely important.
The other problem that orchestrators
overcome is the dynamic environment.
I don't want to especially in the cloud.
I don't want to spin up instances
I don't use.
Right. That's expensive. Right.
And I want to make sure
that I'm tearing down things.
So I don't have
zombie VMs sitting out there just chewing
up, resources and more importantly,
costing me money every, every hour.
Right. Every minute.
So that dynamic, dynamic environment
is, is a key thing that it helps overcome
because the orchestrators
orchestrating across its symphony of,
tools that it has, right?
Symphony of instruments that it has, it's
pulling the right ones in at the right
time.
That's, that's that coordination
that, that they do.
And then the ability to scale up
and have multiple instances
of the same microservice as I need as
I need to dynamically
is, is really important.
And then the last thing that
it really helps with is that consistency.
And reproducibility, which anyone
that's in the DevOps world
or build Meister.
In my good old days we were called
build meisters or configuration managers.
Repeatability of builds,
repeatability of deployment,
and runtime is extremely important.
This gives me that ability to do that
very quickly.
And it helps, avoid any drift
that I might have
by having consistency in the containers.
All right.
Why it all matters.
This one should be very straightforward.
For you guys, reliability
is key. Efficiency.
I want to decrease my cost,
increase developer velocity.
So the developers don't focus on things
that are
easily repeatable,
like setting up an environment.
Right.
Portability
so that I can run this microservice,
this container, anywhere in my ecosystem,
in the cloud, on prem, on my laptop.
I could test things out on my laptop
without having to go into the cloud.
And I can run on any cloud that I want.
And you know, a lot of these.
So a lot of the cloud service providers
out there are going to provide containers
that are very specific to the services
that they connect to in their cloud.
So be careful and be mindful of,
the California Hotel California Syndrome,
where you can check in using
their services but you can't check out.
So spinning your own, images
can sometimes have
a huge advantage over using,
cloud service providers images.
The convenience is there,
but it locks you in.
So you have to weigh the cost
benefit of that, right?
Are you okay saying yes?
We're 100%
AWS or 100% Azure or 100% Google?
Or do I want to run some things on prem?
So you got to make those decisions
early on.
All right.
Okay.
There's some popular orchestrators
there. They're out there.
Everyone's heard of Kubernetes.
They call it an industry standard.
It is kind of by force.
Right.
Google released it on Kubernetes,
is highly configurable, lets
you do things in production,
and lets you configure,
your production
environments, really, really well.
Right.
And because it's highly configurable,
sometimes people say it's a little complex
to set up.
Again, the idea here is for the developer
to be able to quickly and easily
develop their code.
Kubernetes requires a system
admin to get things up and running.
Someone that understands
Kubernetes really well.
There have been some,
what's the right word?
Some permutations of Kubernetes
that tried to simplify its deployment.
Docker, on the other hand,
with Docker Swarm,
their whole premise was easy, simple,
upfront, less configurable.
But it gets a developer
running right away.
No sysadmin required.
Any any
computer scientists, can easily
start up a Docker swarm.
Get it running.
But it's not as configurable.
So you have to adhere to the convention
that they've come up with.
And in some cases that doesn't work
in some production environments
where Kubernetes lets
you configure different things
that will work in different, environments.
Another, general purpose scheduler out
there is Mesos, Apache miso,
slash marathon.
Though
those out there are pretty, pretty good.
We see a lot of the miso stuff
in high performance computing,
is where I've seen it mostly. But,
it's still has it's still has its place.
I think Kubernetes is kind of taking over
the miso space a little bit more.
And then another up and coming is, Nomad,
which Nomad is great for the edge.
Very low profile.
Very similar to Docker Swarm in that,
in that respect
because it focuses on ease of use,
but at the edge,
so it, it's, it's
tailored direct for,
for that extremely lightweight.
And it can happen
multiple workloads very easily.
So if I'm in edge environment
where maybe I only have four gigs of Ram.
So a small footprint
Nomad is a really good, choice for that.
All right.
Some key concepts across
all the orchestrators.
There's a little bit of difference
here, but not not much.
Not much. Cluster. Right.
A cluster is, contains a control
node and a bunch of worker nodes.
That's a that's a cluster. Right?
A node is a host
that's running a container agent.
All these,
all these have agents that run run them.
A pod is for Kubernetes, and a task
is more on the Docker swarm side.
Right.
With a pod there, and we can.
You know what?
We'll save that for Kubernetes.
Deep dive on the difference
between a pod and an individual task.
But they have a new they have a different
abstraction there than in Docker Swarm.
I've got deployments and jobs.
So if I want to deploy something
that's, that
could be running a job to do that
deployment a service.
This is pretty, consistent across
all of them.
It's a stable network endpoint.
A service can be served up
by multiple instances
of a container running,
which is really interesting.
Right?
I've got ingress, which is my
data coming in it.
A lot of times it's used with a gateway
so that external,
applications or external clients
can interface into the networks
of, container network, which we're going
to talk about in another lecture.
Right.
We talked about, config, maps and secrets.
This is my way of storing these secrets.
I don't want to storm any image.
That would be bad,
because anyone that downloaded
my image would have all my certs
and my tokens, so I don't want that.
So this sits on the side.
These secrets and tokens,
are stored in these config maps
and secret vaults and things like that.
And then, for the Kubernetes world,
we've got horizontal,
pod autoscaler,
which will go in more depth,
which is metric driven, scaling.
We'll go more depth
in the Kubernetes, lectures in the future.
And then in Kubernetes,
we use helm charts and operators
that are out there,
which are custom controllers that handle,
kind of the scheduling and control
of individual pods, differently.
So like I said, we'll discuss
those are more Kubernetes.
Focus.
All right.
Now that you understand
some of the terminology,
go out there and explore some more
on orchestration, and find out more.
Get a deeper dive on this by, you know,
consulting with your favorite gin
AI or out there
on, stack space or one of the other,
developer, forums that are out there.
But a lot of people are using,
their
favorite genie AI to help them understand
more, but explore you use those tools
that are out there for you.