All right, let's talk about the docker.
Let's give you an overview of Docker,
the commands that you want to use
and everything.
The theory behind it,
we won't touch on nearly as much.
Let's make this really practical.
How's that sound?
Okay, first off, core concepts.
And then we'll get into,
commands that you can run.
I've got an image
which we've talked about in other,
lectures where an image contains
everything that needs to happen
or in order to run a container.
So it's read
only it's built from a Docker file.
There's different layers in there
that represent file systems, the core,
operating system.
And then the file system changes
throughout, including configuration files.
All that remember images are don't
really contain a state unless you're
storing things in files in the file system
that gets mounted into the image.
A container is a runtime instance
of an image, with its own file system,
its own process space, its own network
interface, and operating environment.
All right.
So you can take a snapshot of a container,
but it's not it's not,
what's the right word?
It's not taking a snapshot
of the running registries
and CPU and memory and all that
that you normally get with like a VM,
right eye containers,
just taking a snapshot of the file system,
the processes,
you know, the file system mostly
because that's
all I can really store inside an image.
Right?
All right.
A Docker file is a script of instructions
to create an image.
And there's some basic, commands inside
these Docker files will show you
a couple of examples from
which means I'm going to inherit
from another base image.
I'm going to run a command.
I'm going to copy files
and an entry point.
It's always some kind of entry point
or command.
Then I'm actually going to run
when I actually run the image to create
a container.
And then there's a registry
which contains all these images.
Most popular out there is Docker Hub,
but a lot of people are hosting their own,
to guarantee the image quality
that they have running in the
in their enterprise organization.
All right.
To install, Docker,
on a mac OS,
you can use homebrew to install Docker.
If you're in Linux, you can do the same.
There's lots of, different,
versions of, installers out there,
depending on the, operating system
that you're using on windows.
Docker
desktop is probably the easiest way to go.
And you want to make sure
that you're enabling, Wizard to,
it's the best operating environment
to run Docker.
Remember Docker containers natively run
in, Linux environments.
They do not run on windows
environments, right?
So on a windows box
you are going to actually
be creating a, wizard to integration,
which is basically just a VM running,
that you're running this stuff in.
Okay.
Let's take a look at a basic workflow
on working with Docker.
The first thing you need to do
is write a Docker container,
or write a Docker file
that gives you a Docker image.
Sorry about that.
So a docker file I have in here from
which is my base image.
In this case I'm grabbing a Node.js,
version 18 or running on alpine.
Right.
I set what my working directory is.
I'm copying some files into the image.
I'm going to run, some commands
to help set up the image.
I'm going to copy more data in.
And then the command I'm going
to run is node and then server dot js.
Remember each one of these commands
the working directory
the copy the run the copy
and command are individual layers.
When building that image.
So pay attention to those layers.
If you have one big long command right,
and you're constantly changing that,
you may want to break that into other
to multiple, run lines in there
so that you're not rebuilding everything
every time.
Then, to build the image.
I just type in Docker build,
dash means tag.
That's
what you're going to name your image
and it's going to pull from that Docker
file.
The, the dot there says
build it from this directory
because I'm copying things
into this image.
The directory that it you do the build in
is important because it's going to look
in the current directory,
for package.json in this case.
Right.
There's other things
you can specify on the command line.
Go ahead and take a look at Docker.
Dash h for help.
And that will help you out some.
All right.
The next thing I'm going to do once
I have that image, what do I want to do?
I want to run that image.
I want to create a container from that.
Right. So it's a Docker run.
And in
this case I do a dash which runs it
as a daemon in the background.
I give the container a name
and then I open up some ports
with the dash P.
It's mapping supports
so that I can actually access this,
Docker container on port 8080.
And then I give the image name.
So there's a container name
and an image name.
Remember container is the runtime.
The image is that thing
I'm going to use over and over again
for each container that that I spin up.
Right.
I can also list
all of the different images that I have
by typing in Docker images.
Or Docker ls will do the same thing, or I
if I want to see
what's running the containers
I have running, I can type in docker.
PS these are very similar commands
that if you're already in the Linux world,
you're going to be very familiar
with a command like ls and PES.
So they kind of mimicked,
they tried their best to mimic
what developers already knew.
All right.
My containers running, everything's
hunky dory.
What if I want to shut it down?
What if I want to, you know,
stop this container.
Well, it's very easy.
I stop it now.
The container will stop, but the container
and the information around
the container will still exist.
Right?
I can inspect,
what's going on inside the container,
but if I leave it there, it will continue
to, can consume,
space on the file system,
it storing container information.
So I want to make sure that I remove that
container.
And I also want to
maybe remove the image as well
if I'm, if I'm done using the image, I'm
not going to use it ever again.
Go ahead and remove the image as well.
That will free up
the resources that you need.
This is especially important
if you're running in the cloud environment
and you're concerned about resources
on an individual VM,
or if I'm spinning up multiple, of these.
Okay, so
so far we've copy data in it at runtime
or at build time.
Right.
What if I have data I want to attach
to a container
that I didn't build into the image?
I have a common image
that I want to use over and over again,
but I want to mount data
into a running container.
They have the concept of something
called a volume.
Now this is not a true blown,
you know, all the way out there, software
defined storage system,
but it gives me a way of mounting data
into a running container.
By creating a volume,
I can create, named volume.
There, and then I can
do the mappings of that volume up
from my current file system at runtime.
So I can say, hey,
the volume is called my data.
And I can either specify how that's being,
what data is going into that volume,
or I can specify at runtime
by saying dash v.
In this case
the volume name,
and then where the data is coming from.
Right.
Slash data in in this case
is where it's getting mounted to.
Right.
So there's that gives you kind of an idea
of how to use volumes.
We'll go more depth on volumes,
but go ahead and research it.
Go ahead and type in Docker volumes.
Dash dash help
and it'll tell you all about it.
So there's some, great,
tips on how to use it effectively.
Right.
So if I, I can actually, create
a, it's a,
it's a bind mount,
so it's an unnamed volume,
which means I'm doing
it just specifically for this container
that I'm not sharing
that volume across containers.
And I can do that at runtime with the dash
V as well.
And I can specify the current working
directory or the directory in the host
that I want mounted into the container
and the container endpoint.
The difference between about a bind
mount point and the named volume is bound.
My, mount points cannot be shared
between containers where volume can.
I can have a container, or a volume.
I mean, that, can be shared
between different containers,
which is an easy way for them to share
a file system or whatever the case may be.
All right.
Let's talk about networking a little bit.
There's a whole lecture on networking.
It's quite a doozy of, of a lecture.
Take a look at it.
The networking,
aspect always seems to be difficult,
in all these systems, because I'm
connecting different things together, and
but let's keep it real simple, with Docker
by default,
it's a bridged network
that gets created, when a container runs,
which means if it's a bridge,
I need to go to port mapping.
So port mapping between the host
and the individual container.
So that's at dash P
that I see all the time
that if I'm going to use the default
I'll do a dash P, the host
IP or the host port colon
the container port.
So if I want to map host port 8080
to container
point 3000 and B 8080 colon 3000.
So anytime anyone from the host accesses
port 8080,
it's going to be mapped to port 30
or 3000 in the, container.
That's the easiest way
to think of a bridge.
That's what a bridge does.
I can define my own bridges,
where I've where I've created
my own bridges that can be used across
multiple, containers,
which can isolate those containers,
right, to use that same bridge.
So that's important when we start thinking
about micro segmentation and things
like that, containers can reside
on these new software defined networks.
This truly, is kind of
rudimentary software defined networking.
We're going to see that
with the Docker world that it can get
even more and more,
complex network architectures.
And so really cool things
when we start talking
Docker Swarm and Kubernetes, where
I'm spanning across multiple hosts
for a host, network,
on Linux only,
I can specify a host network
so that my container can see
the host network as well,
by pulling
by creating a new network on the host
and now
adding that network to the container,
I can now that container now
has access to the host network.
Without that it doesn't
I it's a
so that's that's important to understand.
Okay.
I can
share images in like my repositories
as we talked about before,
they're called registries.
So when I tag when I create my image,
I do a dash t to tag it.
But I can also tag an image
with multiple names
if I want the most common, taxonomy
that people use
is they use the name of the image
and then colon, and then a version.
I see this very common
commonly used out there.
So for in this example
that we're looking at here,
tagging my app latest
because maybe that's what I just built to
my repo, my app colon version one.
So we'll talk about my repo in a second.
But the idea here is that everything
after the colon tends to be,
some kind of version or, yeah.
Yeah, version or,
permutation of the image.
So people can easily
see what they're looking at.
Latest is, is, common vernacular
that everyone uses to say,
this is the latest and greatest
that I've pushed up.
Okay. Now, yeah, I you did notice.
I hope you noticed the name
with my repo on the front.
This is really important
when you start talking about registries.
Because if everyone just pumped everything
into one registry and my app,
and everyone wanted to use my app,
you'd be overwriting each other, right?
If you had the right permissions.
So they have this concept of my repo
so you can specify which repository
you're going to put it in.
And in GitHub you can't push things
into the root repository.
You have to create your own, repository.
And that's the name there.
So in this case my repo is the repository.
My app is the name of the image
in that repository.
And now when I go out
and I'm pulling from that registry,
where I'm actually going to grab that
from the registry, I do a pool
and I can specify the repo
and the image name Docker push
lets me push that image into the repo,
and then docker
pull lets me pull it out so I can share
these images across multiple machines.
By doing this important thing to note,
especially when you're doing
multi machine and Docker
Swarm or Kubernetes,
you have to push your image up into a repo
so the other machines can see it.
Because if you just build an image
on an individual machine,
only that machine can see it.
And if you
want to deploy across
multiple machines in a cluster,
you need to put it
in a registry of some sort.
Okay, let's talk about Docker compose.
This is probably the the foundation
of of running, multiple
images together
to form a set of services.
Because running a microservice, which is
one microservice, is kind of boring.
It's not really a good architecture,
right?
So a lot of times I have many of these
containers that I want to run.
So Docker
compose gives me that ability to specify
the name of the service,
what build I'm using.
Or which I should say which image
I'm going to use, the volumes
I want to connect to it, the ports
I want to open.
I can set up dependencies
between the different services.
So they're spinning up at the right times.
All these all
these different things are involved there.
Take a look at the lecture notes.
You're going to see a lot of Docker
compose.
It's all built on Yaml.
Learn some of the syntax there.
Rely on some of the generative
AI to help you out, but understand what
each one of those things means because
it's going to become very important
as we move into, using Docker
in the cloud more effectively,
it's important to understand
what each of those different layers mean
and how they interact with each other.
Okay, some of the best practices
we want to look at keep your images small.
You see alpine base images.
They're really good images, but they do
require that you install everything.
They don't come with hardly
anything in there. Right.
So some of the things
you're already used to on ubuntu,
if you're using version two or Rhel,
they're not going to be on there.
So you've got to install
every everything that you need.
Look for other images, common
alpine base images.
If you're doing like Node or Python,
there's some really good ones out there
that are very minimal,
that you should be looking at.
So keep your images small.
That way they spin up faster,
they're easier to manage.
Leverage multi-stage builds
to separate build and runtime.
Very important.
Pin your
images with versions to avoid surprises.
So don't always just go to latest,
because if you do and you're pulling
every time that you, you know, do a run,
you could get a side effect.
If there's a new image that's your base
image that you're pulling off of.
So, pin them to specific versions,
if you can,
and then make sure that you're cleaning up
your system to get rid of any old stuff
that's not used anymore.
You can do a Docker system prune,
and it will clean up old images
that aren't used.
They can get there
can be a lot of data in there, right?
Also, make sure that you're storing
your secrets securely.
Avoid EMV, directives in images.
Right.
Because a lot of times
these, dockerfiles get checked in.
Instead, use Docker secrets or use,
HashiCorp vault, to store those secrets.
And you can specify which, you're using
when you run your Docker containers.
Or. All right.
For some further reading
if you want to learn more docs.
Docker.com. Great resource.
They they've got lots of examples up
there.
There's a great book.
From O'Reilly Docker up and running.
Like I said, Docker was designed for
developers for the easy button on there.
And there's lots of great examples
out there.
I'm going to make sure
in the lecture notes
that you have lots of different docker
compose and docker
file, examples out there for you.