this lectures on operating
systems and networks and how they can be.
It's a basic fundamentals on this.
We need to understand this
in order to understand cloud computing and
and what's happening
underneath the covers.
So let's, let's dive right in.
First off, I'm taking,
the information primarily comes in
and even listed some diagrams
from, Cyber Shores operating system book.
And then also on networking on,
cruise
Ross textbook on computer networking.
You can check those out, online
and but they're, they're great resources
for the fundamentals
and even even, some more details on that.
All right.
Let's go over operating systems
real quick.
How a modern, computer works
is really simple.
It's the von Neumann, model
that's been around for decades.
And the basic functionality is still there
where I've got a CPU,
I've got memory or
data, and I've got devices,
and it's
it's really, really simple
when you think about it, a device
can is anything external,
to the CPU and the memory.
And when I talk memory here
this is primarily random access memory.
People go, well, Doctor Darren,
what about,
you know, storage
that's considered a device, right?
There were some disruptions
by having nonvolatile memory.
That's, happening right now.
And, CXL that you can look
into, into those things, the von
Neumann model still fits pretty well.
Well, I have a CPU
that's doing all the work.
I have devices where there's data or input
or a way to send information to a user
or to other computers,
like networking goes through devices.
There's lots of things
in that device realm and then memory.
So what happens is instructions
are put into memory,
whether it's a program or data.
That data is moved
into the cache of the CPU.
The CPU works through that cache, sends
data back out to the memory,
and all that execution happens in CPU.
There are other accelerators
that kind of sit around the CPU
that's still considered, external device
to the CPU, but we're seeing more
and more of these accelerators
put being put directly into the CPU,
that, do things like encryption or AI.
And we're seeing
but the basic model is, is the same.
There's a central processing unit
and expose or extended processing units,
like a math processor or things like that
that are sitting, inside the CPU.
But the basic functionality is the same.
All right.
Traditional computing means that I've got
lots of different devices that I'm now
hooking up to the CPU to get information
into the CPU or into memory.
But the idea here is even a GPU
needs a CPU in order to do the work
that the CPU is orchestrating.
The other accelerators that are out there
most of the time.
Right.
And the idea here
is that all these external, devices
that I have have
some kind of controller in the middle,
even the graphics, adapter is in there,
but they're all
they they're all talking to the CPU,
which is orchestrating everything.
All right,
let's talk about operating systems.
So when a program gets,
put into a computer, it really is sitting
in some kind of,
a storage, at first,
and then it gets put into memory,
then that, the CPU is notified.
Hey, there's a program that wants to run.
Here's its memory location with the data.
It may have pointers back into, storage,
which we'll talk about virtual memory
and things like that.
But the idea here is that the program
acts as an intermediary
between the user and the computer.
Right. Those are all your instructions.
And the goal of the operating system
is to execute
those user programs and,
and solve the problems for the users
and handle all of the,
device management
and orchestrate moving data
to memory
or from devices and back and forth.
The operating system handles
all that for you.
Before we had operating systems,
programmers would have to do all of that,
which means the programs
are really fast, right?
Because they weren't doing anything
except what the user specified.
However, it took a long time.
You had to know a lot about a lot
of the different devices and all that.
So the operating system orchestrates
all of that, and many times
most operating systems are dealing
with several different,
programs running at the same time.
So it's handling conflicts between,
oh, someone needs the disk now.
Someone needs a monitor now.
Sony.
Oh, I need oh, someone interrupted me
with a keyboard there.
The operating system
handles all that for you.
So as I mentioned,
the operating system is a resource
allocator.
It manages
all the resources on the computer.
It decides, between conflicting results.
And it is a control program.
If you're on a Linux box
and we'll see this, it has a process
ID of one is typically what you find.
That's the init script
that kicks things off.
And there's other helper processes
in the operating system.
But the idea here is that it controls
execution of programs and prevents
errors and prevents conflicts.
Between multiple programs
running at the same time.
And it gives you proper
use of the computer.
And operating systems
today are pretty robust.
And, and we're seeing some new changes
in operating systems,
but they're pretty stable,
for, for the most part.
All right.
Let's talk about interrupt.
So an interrupt is, when I get an event,
that is happening in the CPU that stops
what's currently happening
and then, makes a decision
on what to do next.
So an interrupt could be a keystroke.
It could be,
Yeah, several.
It could be a page fault.
There's so many things
it could be an IO event that comes in.
The idea here is that incoming interrupts,
can be disabled
when another interrupt is being processed.
And this prevents, interrupts
from being lost.
All right, so a trap is a software
generated interrupt
that I can do in in code.
And it's used.
It's it's typically there,
to designate
an error happened or something like that,
or have a user request or something
like that, a software trap.
Okay.
The operating system can be,
interrupted through traps
or hardware interrupts.
There's lots of different interrupts
that are in the system.
Great example of a type of interrupt
is I plug in a USB key
or a new, keyboard into, a computer.
I get an interrupt.
Hey, a new device has
been added, or I add a new,
monitor.
Anything. Right.
That's a hardware type of interrupt.
But I can also have IR interrupts.
Where, maybe I've got,
I want to go request some memory,
and it just wasn't there.
Right.
A memory fault, type of thing.
So lots of different interrupts.
And they're important
in the operating system.
Has to understand what to do
with those interrupts and act appropriate.