All right.
Let's talk about process management
and how the operating system works
with processes.
This is one of the most important things
that a operating system
does is work with these programs,
which are put into processes.
There's a variety of different types
of programs that are out there.
Batch systems which primarily are your big
mainframe types of things?
They call the term jobs
on timecard systems, which all of us have.
It's typically user programs or tasks
that are working on,
a lot of textbooks use the terms
job and process interchangeably.
That's that's perfectly fine. Right?
Because for what we're working with, right
now, that's,
probably the best way to think about it.
A process,
though, is a program of execution
and a process must process
in sequential fashion.
A process includes a program counter,
stack, data section for processing,
concepts.
People say, yeah,
but I just wrote a program that does,
that's multithreaded.
And those are considered processes.
When you look at the process
queue, you'll, you'll see that
there's micro or some processes
that are, that are running off of that
to handle all the different threads.
All right.
So let's talk about process in memory
first off.
So a process itself
when I look at the memory for a program
it has these four key elements.
Right.
There's actually a fifth one user data.
But we can talk about that.
First is the stack.
This is a region containing the function
call stack and local variables
and temporary data so that your stack,
the heap is dynamic memory allocated
allocation region
for objects in data structures.
So your heap is
where most of your, memory is going.
That is, beyond just the local variables
or registers and temporary data
and things like things like that.
Your data,
this is containing
global variables and static data
initialized by the program.
And then text is the program instructions.
Write your stack
which has the call functions.
And the
it knows how to reach into your text
where your program instructions
are, and pull from that and put them,
into the proper order in the call stack.
Right. Basics of of memory.
There
you see a region in the middle there.
And we'll talk about that,
that region here in a little bit.
But let's take a look at process state.
Because all processes have state
very simple.
They may be a little bit different
from operating system to operating system.
But the core concepts are the same.
When a process gets created,
it's in the new state.
It gets admitted to
to, it
gets admitted to be put into the CPU.
It moves to a ready state
until it actually gets,
dispatched, for the scheduler.
And now it's running and instructions
are being executed when it's running,
then a process, if it gets interrupted,
the process can move to a waiting state.
Maybe another process comes in
and needs something, or it's waiting on,
IO input output.
Whatever the case may be, it moves into,
a waiting state,
and then it's
sitting there in the waiting state
until it gets scheduled,
for dispatch again.
And then it's running again
until it terminates.
So it's pretty straightforward.
What you'll find it, though, is
that process is constantly moved between
the running and the, waiting.
And then ready state that running.
Waiting. Ready.
State it.
It spins in that quite a bit,
especially if you have a program
that's highly reliant on IO,
which you will find.
Maybe you say, well,
I don't hit the disk or but you'll find
that even waiting for memory
sometimes, can be something that,
you get interrupted and maybe you need io,
right?
Right.
That's memory outside of, just the memory.
That's, in in the CPU at the time.
So that state there
ready, running, waiting.
That's, very common
that you'll see your process in.
All right.
A process control block.
So this is information
associated with each process.
This is kind of in the in
while it's in the process control block.
There you go.
It's almost like a header there.
You've got the process state.
Every process has an ID or number.
A program counter
where I am in my program, registers.
So these are the CPU registers.
Remember the process control block?
I've got to store all this stuff.
So when I go back into the ready state,
I can continue where I left off.
So I gotta store
all my registers in there.
Any memory limits that I might have?
List of open file.
So any state that I need.
Right, in order to come back from,
ready to running.
So when I go into waiting, I capture
the state from the CPU stored in memory.
In this process control block,
move in to waiting,
and then, and already.
And then from there, it's going to reload
all this stuff back into, the CPU.
Okay.
So process creation.
So there is a process process number one
that is the parent process
of all the other processes.
This is your init script.
And it will create children processes
which in turn can create children
or grandchildren or great grandchildren
processes that form a process tree.
Generally, processes are identified
and managed via
something called a PID or a process ID,
and you'll see this
especially in Linux and Unix systems,
where
if you run PPS, which stands for process,
you can see all the
PIDs have all your processes
that are running,
and there's other information
you can find, with, with PPS as well.
Another program that a lot of people
use is Top, which continually updates.
And you can see your processes
that are in the, ready
queue or running or waiting queues.
You can see all that,
which is kind of cool.
You can look and see what your, operating
system is doing with all your processes.
Remember that, processes,
can actually share resources,
between parent and children.
They can share all, all the resources
that the parent has, the child
has. And, children can share a subset
of the parent's resources
and parent and children,
share.
No, no resources.
Those are three different, options
that you have when you're spinning out
a, some process.
Okay, execution.
When the parent and children
execute, concurrently,
the parent can wait for children
to terminate.
But for, until,
children terminate for process creation,
there's a whole bunch of different options
there that you can, set up
in the operating system. So.
But the idea here is that the parent
process, spins out or creates the children
processes, and there is a relationship
there that you need to understand.
And how they share resources
and their execution paths.
If you
do care,
depending on how you haven't set up,
if you kill the parent process,
it will kill the children process.
So you don't have zombie processes
sitting out there.
That's an OS thing
and also a program thing.
If you're programing in lower
level languages like C and C plus plus,
you can actually specify,
that kind of relationship.
All right.
Here's an example process tree on Linux.
Here I run a piece and with some options
there to show you, more what's going on.
You can see here
that the root user has process ID one.
And then there's a whole bunch of other,
things that are running there
that are all underneath that,
that process.
Process one,
all those are launched by the init script.
Right?
And those are operating system processes
that are keeping track of what's going on.
They do have some
operating systems
that are even pared down even further.
And these are really great
for like real time operating systems
where you want a minimal amount of,
context switching
or a process,
conflicts, running.
So they, they pare things down
really tight because I want to do,
do something very specific.
Okay.
When I launch, let's talk about process
creation some more on the address space.
So depending on how I launch the process,
again through a programing language,
I can get a full duplication of the parent
address space.
That it's loaded in.
Right.
So I can do that with a fork
where it creates a new process or.
Exactly.
Which is used after fork
to replace memory space
with a new program, program
process creation.
So it's important here
to understand the differences.
You either copy the whole address space,
from the parent
into the child or,
or it creates its own head.
So understanding
the difference can be very important,
especially if you have a really
large program and maybe you're firing off
a bunch of smaller, you're forking off
a bunch of smaller programs
to do something.
Remember that you're taking
that address space, with you.
All right.
Let's talk about single
threaded and multithreaded processes.
There is a difference
in running a subprocess.
Then a thread,
and most of it has to do with the,
the code, a data and file information
in that, in that process, control block.
Right.
So for single threaded, single threaded,
there's one set of code,
one set of data, one set of files,
the register,
the stack, all that is single threaded.
And I'm running on one thread
in the processor.
Just that. That's it.
With multi-threaded what happens is
I split and I create multiple threads.
The code data and files are the same,
but registers
and stack are separate from each other.
So these processes can run in.
They appear to be running in parallel and
on multicore and multi-threaded machines.
They do a really good job at,
allocating the resources appropriately
so they are running in parallel
so you can get a lot faster.
By going
multi-threaded, you
can get a lot more performance out of it,
but your bottleneck can still be the code
and data and files.
If I'm doing a subprocess, then
I'm copying the code data and files,
which means I'm not sharing those anymore.
But there are fewer conflicts. So.
But if you need to share information
between two processes like that
multi-threaded handles
most of that for you.
There are techniques to share information
through shared memory,
or moving data back and forth
between processes that we can talk about,
but that is slower.
All right.
Let's talk about the scheduler here
real quick.
The CPU scheduler is the thing
that's selecting
when processes get to run or threads
you know
get get deployed inside the CPU,
CPU scheduling decisions, may take place
when a process switches from running to,
waiting state
and from running to ready state
or switches from,
waiting to ready or terminate.
So scheduling decisions are happening
all the time in that tight little circle
of that running, waiting, ready, running,
reading, ready to terminate.
Right? If it terminates.
And I don't
I don't need to put that in there anymore.
What's critical here is in,
in the running
to waiting state and the terminate state,
they're non pre preemptive.
So I can't preempt something
as I'm moving from the running
to the waiting state
I need to capture that that
process control block and then terminate
I can't preempt the terminate.
Okay.
All the other scheduling in the CPU
is, preemptive.
All right.
I mentioned the word context switch.
Let's understand what it means. Right?
When a CPU switches
from one process to another,
the system has to save that state.
And that process control block,
which saves the state,
the registers, open files, all that stuff
and saves that state, and then introduces
another process and loads
that state into the CPU.
If I have a, CPU,
that's context switching a lot,
it will slow things down.
Right. And that's an overhead.
So you want to decrease context switching
as much as possible.
What you find, especially in cloud
computing, because you are doing
a shared resource with other, programs
that are out there.
You don't know what they're running.
And context switching can really cause
a lot of problems for you, right?
Whether it's IO that's blocking and oh,
now this other program gets get
gets in there
if you if you context switch a lot,
you can actually, overwhelm the CPU.
Great news is, is the operating systems
handle that pretty well.
Now nowadays
if you're running in real time
operating systems,
you can absolutely see the lag
when you have too many, programs
running at the same time.
And that context switch is overhead.
All right.
So, be mindful of that when you're
programing in, in these systems.
Also be mindful of context switching
when you're working too.
If you're context switching a lot
changing state and things like that,
it can be hard to keep track of things
as humans,
sometimes
have a hard time with context switching.
All right.
The dispatcher module controls the CPU.
And, it's a short term scheduler.
For switching contexts,
switching the user mode,
jumping to the proper location
in the user program
when things get started,
that's the dispatcher.
When I move from that,
ready state into the process state,
there's some things
that have to happen in in there,
and there's some dispatch latency.
You're not going to see.
I did so fast in the CPUs today.
You're not going to see that, very often.
But it's good to know
that it exists in there.
All right, CPU, scheduling criteria.
There are lots of different,
criteria out there in the operating
system, in the schedule scheduler.
And some of it depends
on the operating system that you're using.
But most of them, for general purpose,
I use, pretty standard.
Scheduling algorithms
that are out there today with the goal
of keeping the CPU as busy as possible.
If there are a bunch of programs
sitting out there that are waiting.
I don't want that. Right?
I want to I want, to, service
as many processes as I can.
Throughput is, possible criteria
that I'm looking at
or turnaround
time, waiting time and response.
And all these things
have have a role in these schedulers.
Scheduling
algorithms are pretty well known
and but we do see some, modern, CPU,
architectures
that, can change some of the scheduling
and make, the schedulers even more,
optimized through, feedback
loops from the CPU.
So those are some interesting
things to understand.