All right.
Let's talk about memory management
in the operating system.
This is an important aspect
because if you can't get
data into the CPU, it won't do anything.
So that's what it basically comes down to.
So all data goes into the memory before
and after processing.
So that memory becomes very important.
Right.
And remember memory is storing bits
and bytes
in, in some kind of fashion,
which basically on and off switches.
Think of that,
that I'm sending into the CPU
so it knows what to do
and what data to operate on.
So that memory becomes
extremely important.
All instructions are in memory
before they execute.
Memory management determines,
what is in memory.
When I'm optimizing the CPU
and computer responds
to users, main memory management
activities are extremely important.
So this is what they are
keeping track of which parts of memory
are currently being used and by whom.
Deciding which processes or parts
of those processes and data, and move in
and out of memory, and then allocating
and allocating memory spaces as needed.
Now there was a big movement
about ten years ago
in, of the mid 20 teens
for, nonvolatile persistent memory.
Well, this is this is very interesting
because it was throwing the von Neumann
model kind of on its ear
a little bit where,
memory was becoming so large
that I had enough memory,
that I didn't need,
virtual memory and things like that,
which we'll talk about a little bit about.
So it was, changing
kind of things on their ear
where processes now float around.
Memory and processes are allocated
to memory locations
instead of the other way around.
That has gone a little sideways,
with CXL, and so take a look.
Take a look at that.
There could be some interesting
new changes to operating systems
and the traditional computing model
in the future around memory.
Specifically,
which I think is very exciting.
All right.
Let's take a look at the difference
between logical and physical memory.
Physical memory
that's a physical storage
device is typically divided into fixed
size blocks called frames,
always in the power of two
between 5 and 12 bytes and eight by ten.
In some cases larger.
Now and then, logical memory
is divided
into physical blocks called pages.
So in a physical they're called frames.
In the logical
we call them pages and pages
divided into two parts user memory
and kernel memory.
User memory for the user program
and kernel memory contains
kernel programs and data for things
in the operating system.
Right user
memory is divided into two parts.
The text that contains instructions
for the user
and the other
the other memory that you'll see in there.
But the user.
You'll
what we'll show you in a little bit.
All right.
There's something in, memory management
called the memory management
Unit or the MMU.
It's a hardware device that translates
logical addresses to physical addresses.
So there's an abstraction there
so that I'm not connected
directly to physical addresses.
It's all through the MMU, right.
So that logical maps pages to frames.
All right.
There's three types of minimum use.
There's segmented pages and TLB.
User programs deal with logical addresses
not physical addresses.
The IMU translate
the logical addresses to the physical
and then translates
the physical addresses to frames.
And then
those frames get translated to pages
and translates pages back to user memory.
So it sounds a little complicated.
And and and it can be
memory management can be very complicated.
But the idea here
is that the program itself
knows about logical addresses.
The IMU is translating the logical pages
to frames.
That's that's the key behind us
okay. Paging.
So because I'm translating frames to page
we call it paging right.
That's where a local address
space of a process can be noncontiguous
in the physical memory.
It doesn't have to all be laid out.
You know, in this cell inside
the cell can.
Right?
It can be split across, multiple frames.
It divides
the physical in into multiple chains.
Remember
we have the five, 12 and eight K frames.
Right.
And the idea is that, I'm allocating
those frames that those frames get,
fixed size,
based off of the type of operating system
I have or the type of machine
that I'm running on.
That can make a big difference
in, how many,
frames I'm pulling in when I'm
pulling programs in.
Okay.
The idea is that the IMU is keeping
track of all the free frames,
so it knows where in memory
I can put things.
And, it handles,
making sure that I can fit my program
in a certain number of, pages,
that I have that map to those frames.
Right.
So it sets up this page table
to translate the,
the logical the physical addresses.
As you can see, I can have what we call
fragmentation, where let's say
that I've got a logical memory.
Page 0123.
My page table sits there and says, well,
that's one, four, three and seven frames.
And they're scattered throughout. Memory.
Now, if I have multiple memory chips,
which most program, most, big computers
in your data centers and cloud have,
then I can actually,
get better throughput,
by spreading my, logical addresses
across multiple, memory, chips.
If the chip is the problem, a lot of times
your bus is the problem.
But there's lots of different,
strategies around this.
And the great thing is, is
you don't have to worry about that.
The IMU is doing that for you
to optimize performance.
It's built into the algorithm. So the IMU
all right
I can have shared pages shared page.
Typically it's it's read
only type of code.
So if I, if I'm loading
code up into memory,
it'll typically be put into a shared,
shared page.
Because I want, multiple processes
maybe to use that same,
memory space, especially if I'm launching
a children processes.
There's a lot of shared pages and children
in parent processes.
So think of it that way.
So I'm sharing the same location
in logical address space
with multiple processes.
I can have private,
not shared pages, private code.
Each process keeps its own separate copy.
Those I don't
I don't want to share it back and forth.
Right.
So but realize if I can have shared pages,
which is kind of nice
because I'm not allocating as much memory
in the physical memory to do that,
which means I can run a lot of programs
that maybe have shared libraries and are.
The advent of shared
libraries was so awesome back in the 90s
when we first had those shared libraries.
It meant that
when I have multiple programs,
it's using maybe the same math library.
I don't have to load that math library
into memory.
For every single program,
it's just I load it
once and everyone gets to use it,
which is kind of nice.
So that that's one of the reasons
why I can run so many programs
on an operating system
that have far more, resources
that are required to run that program,
because there's a lot of shared, memory
that are going
on, through these shared pages.
All right.
Virtual memory, here's another way
that you can get more memory on your box
than you have Ram.
It's through
something called virtual memory.
Now, virtual memory separates the user
logical memory from the physical memory,
which we've already talked about,
but only a part of the program
gets put into, the physical memory.
And I can have, that virtual memory
that is another layer with another table
that says, here's
where all of the, information lies.
But instead of lying in Ram,
which is expensive,
I can put it on to, cheaper storage,
like a solid state drive or an NVMe drive,
whatever, whatever the case may be.
And we were seeing something
with virtual memory, with,
technology like Optane from
Intel or CXL,
where now I've got a lot cheaper memory
and there's several stages,
of memory tiers that I can put things,
but believe me, programmers
always have a way of expanding
their programs larger
than the amount of Ram that they have.
Their box.
I was programing,
when Optane first came out.
I got, my hands on about six
terabytes of,
nonvolatile memory,
and I thought, there's no way I'll.
I'll use all that memory I did.
I found a way to use it all.
So as programmers,
we have a way of, writing
highly inefficient code
that requires virtual memory.
So as much memory as you got,
we'll we'll take it all up.
So the idea here is that virtual memory
can expand, right?
How much memory
I have by storing things on other medium.
And it allows the address spaces
to be shared across multiple processes
and across, much larger than the address
space that I actually have.
But there's overhead to it,
right?
I add another memory map that I have.
Right.
So the MMU, I have my virtual memory,
in it, it's very similar,
but it's, it's yet another map.
Right.
So I've got my, my virtual memory there,
which with pages I've got memory maps
that go into, my,
in my, logical maps
that then go into the physical map.
So and I'm moving data
between the storage and the memory,
constantly with this,
which means IO hits.
Oh, no, I'm hitting my IO bus.
So, if you're in real time
systems, this
this will slow some things down.
All right?
So be mindful.
Mindful of this,
on those real time systems.
All right.
Virtual address
space means that my program can grow
much, bigger than the memory space.
It's there.
So when we talked about, the, the program
or the process space
and all the memory in the process space,
it includes that virtual address
space now, which is in between the stack
and the heap, which was that blue area
that we talked about in previous lecture.
This area here, it allows me to grow
much larger than the than the actual
a space that I have available.
But remember I'm using
virtual address space which can be slower.
So ideally you want your programs
to not chew up too much memory
because you are going to thrash
and the IO bus,
for, for having all that
most the time today.
You may you may see that happen
the most time to the operating systems
do a pretty good job at,
handling this, for you.
But a lot of them allocate, disk, space
for virtual memory right upfront
when they install.
And you don't even know,
you may have a terabyte drive
and there may be 100 gig, or more,
sitting there in the virtual address
space used to be, more
visible, but, mostly operating systems
are hidden out away from, you know.
All right.
Let's talk about demand paging.
So this is
when I bring a page into memory.
And I want to make sure
that I'm only bringing pages into memory
at the appropriate time. Right.
Because I don't
I have limited resources there.
So these schedulers have to know
the, the right time to bring stuff in.
So I want to bring memory
only when it's needed.
Because there's less IO that needs to come
in, there's less memory
needed, a faster response,
and I can handle more users.
So shared pages are going to take
priority, obviously,
because I have a bunch of processes
running. Right.
When a page is needed, typically,
a program will throw an alert or abort.
Hey, I tried to access something
that's not in memory.
Oh, it's in virtual memory.
So I'll actually get an interrupt
that will then tell the IMU.
Hey, you got to go fetch this page
and bring it into memory.
Okay? That's how it works.
There's also a lazy swapper, technique,
which I'll never swap pages out
until I do get a fault.
And then there's more on demand or,
not on demand, but preemptive,
where The swapper will try and add pages
preemptively, predicting what's needed.
Okay.
As I already mentioned before,
when I'm paging memory, I'm
bringing it from the drive, the,
the slower memory into main memory.
Right.
Which, remember,
I still have the page and the frames.
Right?
So it's got to go through the IMU
to handle that so I can swap.
If I need more room, I can swap
a whole program out where I'm going to go
store that into the virtual memory
and then swap in on the program.
So you can see I'm hitting the IO
bus twice to do this.
So page swaps can be, very expensive.
But when we're talking at the speeds,
we're talking at five and six gigahertz,
you're not going to notice that
unless you're doing it a lot.
I mentioned page fault.
Page faults
means that I'm trying to access memory
that's not in the physical memory,
which means it's going to go and,
tell the operating system
this program now goes into a well,
you guessed it right, a state.
Right.
So that process, if it gets a page file,
the memory goes into the wait state, it's
going to go do some IO things,
put it back into the ready state, and then
once the memory is loaded, it
will then say,
hey, you're actually ready to do
do this work.
And it goes back into the scheduler.
The have to have things happen, right?
So that process so you really don't
want something that's hitting
virtual memory a lot, right?
It will it will slow down right.
Okay.
Copy on right.
This allows both the parent
and the child process to initially share
the pages in memory.
If the process modifies the shared page
then only a copy is saved.
So this is it.
This saves on memory quite a bit
because maybe I'm reading memory
and I'm just reading the values there,
but I'm not changing anything
in that block of memory.
Then, I don't need to make a full copy.
I only need to make,
changes to the memory.
This frees up a lot of memory, and,
it frees up, a lot of that,
thrashing that you get from bringing
in, virtual pages.
Here's a here's a big problem.
Right?
What if there is no free memory?
I can't bring anything in.
Well, what's going to happen?
Well,
I've got to swap something out,
so I have to make a decision.
Who am I going to interrupt?
Am I going to interrupt someone else?
And am I at a higher priority?
This is where the scheduler
and the algorithms
that are in the schedulers do their magic,
their black magic here.
Right?
They have to make decisions on, well,
whose memory am I going to swap out?
Maybe I've got a process sitting there.
I've got memory
that hasn't really been used in a while.
No one's read it, no one's.
So maybe I'm going to get rid of that.
But who knows,
maybe the next process needed.
All that memory
now is going to swap back in.
There's lots of different algorithms
that are out there to to make this,
more effective. So,
but you can see a page
going in and out
of, in and out of, virtual memory a lot.
So these are things
that some of the more modern,
modern schedulers are doing.
And there's been some great research
and there's some really cool new AI stuff
that is handling, memory,
more effectively,
especially in programs like Java
that are running because they do their own
garbage collection.
So understanding,
how their freeing memory can actually,
help me, quite a bit.
In fact, some of these new schedulers
are sitting beside the current scheduler
and making the schedulers more,
more predictive
on, when memory needs to come in and not,
which,
we're seeing some vast improvements,
like 70% performance improvement.
That's huge.
So, this is
this is a hot area of research
and, some good areas,
that people may want to, work in,
patch replacement.
We've talked a little bit about this.
I want to prevent
overall allocation of memory.
By modifying page file routines.
And so I want to make sure that I'm doing
the right things at the right time,
that I'm replacing the right pages.
So that I
in optimizing for everyone
running on a machine or maybe,
maybe into individual, applications
that maybe have a higher priority, right?
Large virtual memory
can provide a smaller physical memory.
As we've already talked, I can
maybe only have 16 gig of Ram on my box,
but I can have an address
space of a terabyte.
Now, that would mean a lot of swapping,
which could slow me down.
Right.
So you gotta find the
right balance for, the work.