All right.
Quickly, we're going to talk about,
the nuts and bolts of the internet.
This is going to be a acronym soup.
Today, because, we got to understand
a little bit of the, networks
and the internet architecture.
To understand distributed systems,
especially in cloud.
After all, clouds are all networked
together, how we interact with them.
So it might it's not might
it is important that we understand,
kind of, the verbiage,
the words that are used
when we talk about internet
and how it came about.
And, and remember,
the internet's all about communicating
it across, a network of machines
that can be all over the world.
So this when you think about it, it's
pretty darn cool when you think about,
the internet right
there, using machines all over the world.
So let's talk about some of the background
and where it came from.
What is the internet?
It's not a bunch of tubes.
No, as someone famous said,
no, it's
a network of interconnected devices
which can be your PC servers,
mobile devices,
all running applications and services,
all sharing information between each other
through, connected infrastructure
and understanding
all that connected infrastructure.
That's what we're going to talk about
in the next couple lectures, right?
So first off, communication links.
How are things connected
that physical media.
There's lots of different ways fiber
I wish I had fiber in my house.
That would be so cool.
Copper is probably the most, prevalent.
And well, at least in, in some countries.
Believe it or not, most pavilion over
the world is radio waves.
Wow. Radio waves. Right.
And satellites.
We're starting to see a big amount
of satellite usage for internet,
but they're all characterized
by something called bandwidth.
Bandwidth is how much data can I push
through every second?
That's your data transmission rate.
That's your bandwidth, right?
I want as much bandwidth as I can get.
Right.
Because I can move data in and out faster
in between my machine and another machine
somewhere else in the world.
What connects all these, together
are network switches and routers.
So we're going to talk a little bit
about the difference between these
and what they do
and how they connect to each other.
But the idea is this
is that these networks, which is in
routers, they forward packets
between connected devices.
So if I say, hey,
I want some information from
my cloud instance
that's running in, India,
I've got I send out a request to
my router.
Here it goes. Oh, you're asking for this?
I know another router
that knows how to get access to that.
So it sends that information
out to that router.
That router goes I gotcha.
It sends it to another router
which sends it
to a computer somewhere else.
And that gives me the information,
then sends it back to set of routers.
Could be the same routers
or different routers.
Back to to to give me the information.
It's really incredible.
Oh, it's amazingly incredible
right how this all works.
But that enables data flow
between different
computers and different devices out there.
There's something called internet service
providers.
These are the people that are
providing the internet
to individuals and businesses.
When, the internet first kicked off,
it wasn't it was Arpanet.
When it first kicked off, there weren't
any internet service providers.
There were network providers. Right.
And these,
these big, government and financial,
government
and academia institutions connected their
networks
together, connected their machines
together across long distances,
which, started this whole thing.
And now, it's pervasive. It's everywhere.
You can get the internet.
I've been traveling a lot lately,
and I can get the internet anywhere,
even on the airplane.
I can get the the internet,
which is, really incredible.
Okay, think of the internet
as as it's grown up,
as a network of networks,
it's interconnected internet service
providers and institutions.
Right.
In order to make this work,
we had to have some standardization
or protocols
for sending and receiving messages.
Some of these you may recognize TCP,
IP, http.
Skype was a protocol around 211.
These are all different standards.
You should look them
up, learn more about them.
Internet standards that are out.
Those are protocols.
Internet standards that are out
there come primarily
through two major organizations.
To RFC request for comments on the IETF,
which is the Internet Engineering Task
Force.
It's been around a long time.
They come up with many of the internet,
standards that are out there today.
Here are some other, I said acronym soup.
Here you go.
Here's some acronym soup for you,
domain Name service DNS.
This is as you notice,
humans like names, computers like numbers.
DNS is a name to number mapping.
So if I want to go to google.com,
which I know is 8.8.8.8,
look, I'm a, domain name, so, service
Tony if I'm on that,
because I knew that
google.com maps to 8.8.8.
So that's
an IP address and internet
protocol address.
Right.
Which is IP stands for not intellectual
property by Internet Protocol.
And then Http Hypertext Transfer
Protocol,
SNMp, SMTp,
which is a mail transfer protocol.
Simple.
And then FTP has been around a long time
feel file transfer protocol.
So anything that ends in TP,
you're going to be it's
probably transfer protocol something.
Right.
So keep that in mind
when you're talking about the internet.