All right, let's talk about internet
architecture.
We talk about nuts and bolts.
In a previous, lecture,
just kind of acronym soup.
Let's talk
about the actual architecture now.
So first off, let's take, a view
of the internet from a service view.
All right.
What does the internet really provide
for me?
What services?
Does it provide for me as an individual
and also to applications?
Well, provides a lot, right?
It provides,
the world Wide Web, voice over IP, email,
games, e-commerce, social networks,
the list goes on and on,
especially for an application where maybe
I want to tap into all that information.
It provides an, programable,
interface to all those applications
that are out there.
So it's not just the network
and the physical stuff.
There's also, the concept
and we talked about the rest interface
in previous lectures.
There's also this concept of providing
an API,
and ways that I can connect
to the internet and the services
on the internet that are out there.
It's very analogous to the Postal Service,
in that I don't know how my mail gets from
one place to another, or a message
gets from one place to another.
I just know that it happens.
All right.
So it's becomes ubiquitous.
It's pretty prevailing everywhere
and easy to use for anyone.
All right.
So let's take a closer look
at the network structure a little bit.
We can break the network, down
into, three major groups,
the network edge,
which most of you are dealing in the edge.
These are host machines and client servers
and in data centers, things like that.
That's what they call the network edge.
At my house,
it can be a whole bunch of smart, devices
that I have,
like the lock on my front door
or the lights in the house
or cameras, all that stuff.
That's that network edge
all connected to the internet.
That's the extreme, dynamic
or the extreme edge out there.
There's some dynamic edge,
which could be your cell phone.
You're moving around
connecting to different networks
dynamically all the time.
Kind of crazy
when you think about it. Right.
Then there's access networks.
This is physical media.
These are wireless communications
and wired communications
separate from the network edge.
Because, as I mentioned, my cell phone
can connect to a tower in California
where I live, or in Saudi Arabia
where I just was.
My device is the same,
but it's connecting to different access
networks, throughout.
So that's
how I'm connecting into the internet.
And then the network core
is the interconnected routers
that make up this network of networks
that are out there.
Access networks and,
how do I connect to systems
through an edge router?
That's that's, critical.
Right.
If I'm at home, I could have, a Wi-Fi.
That's that's, access
to a physical to the internet,
through my Wi-Fi.
Institutional access could be, plugging
in at work or at school.
And then also when I'm out and about,
just connecting to a mobile network
now connects me through maybe, 5G
or, LTE.
Heaven forbid it's still LTE for you.
It's a little bit slower
because of bandwidth, right?
I want as much bandwidth
as I possibly can,
which are the bits
per second of access to a network.
And, do I have a dedicated line
or, physical or shared line?
At my house, I have both a dedicated line
and a shared line.
Shared line.
I get more bandwidth, but I'm sharing it
with a bunch of other people
right in my neighborhood.
My dedicated line.
I'm guaranteed a certain amount
of bandwidth because I'm on the only.
I'm the only one on that one.
But it's not as much bandwidth,
but it's more reliable.
So there's lots of there's lots to go
on in in this internet thing.
All right.
Let's talk about the network core.
Right.
This is a mess of interconnected routers.
And the idea here
is that these routers know
where to direct packets,
a packet, it's just like, Postal service.
I've got a package that I'm sending
from my house to maybe my parents house.
Right.
How many post offices doesn't
need to go through to get there?
That's the same sort of thing
with the network core.
Each router can be considered
a post office.
And,
there's a little a number attached to,
where you're trying to get to
or send the package to.
And, these, routers know where to send it
because I don't know how to handle this.
I'm going to send it to my pal over here
because I think he knows how to handle it.
And then maybe he
he knows how to handle it.
And he he goes
on. Now, remember, it's a hierarchy.
So it's it's going to, hit
probably more than two routers
when you're routing across the world.
But each packet is transmitted,
at a four link capacity.
It's going to try and forward that package
or that packet to the next router
until it finds the right router
that it belongs to.
And then once it hits that post office,
it will deliver it to the network
edge, to the device that says, hey, here
I am.
Right.
And so that's the
idea behind the network core.
The idea that it's a
network of networks is really important.
Because these are all independent
networks,
which is really crazy that we've been able
to do, create something.
So, attached
and so, I what's your right word?
This, this world that we have
with all these political beliefs
and all these different things
that we can connect a bunch of routers
together and we can all agree
that, hey, we're going to move things,
move things along.
Right?
So these internet service providers,
they're all connected together.
Residential company universities
are all they're all connected
in this network of networks.
Like I mentioned before, these packets
are being routed between these routers,
which are owned by lots of different,
companies, which is amazing as well.
And, it's, it's resulted
in, a vast, complex network
that, sometimes gets, sensor.
I don't want all packets
coming into my country.
Someone might say,
but overall it's it's really incredible
that we've been able to do this.
All right.
Let's take a look at a couple pictures
on how this how this really works.
Right.
It would be interesting
if there was a global internet
service provider.
But, the ramifications of that,
as I've already said,
would be really, really hard, right?
Because who's going to control
the whole internet and who wants someone
to have that much control? Instead?
It's a federation
of a bunch of regional networks
or a network of network, system
where I'm I'm sharing.
Hey, I've got routing information here.
I'll take your packets type of thing.
This still gives governments
the ability to monitor
and, censor the information
coming into their countries, people,
that are all about
freedom of of information don't like that.
But without that capability,
I don't think the internet
would have spread as quickly as it has.
And we're seeing more and more,
techniques
to share information across,
this vast internet that we have.
It's still amazing that it exists.
Right.
I'm sitting
on top of this network of networks.
We're seeing things like content provider
networks.
This is where I'm providing actual content
across the network.
Google, Microsoft.
Akamai.
Tencent.
These are these are big content providers,
that are providing information
across this whole network.
And it's it's really amazing
that they can all work together
in this, kind of weird.
It's but,
you know, maybe someone should sit back
and do a poli sci,
a dissertation on the growth of,
the internet,
because it's really, truly amazing.
How much information is being shared
across the world?
In this, technical, technically,
very viable, politically amazing
that had happened type of,