All right.
Let's talk about a
layered approach to the internet
and how how it works, how it works.
Let's go back to the Postal Service.
We talked about it before.
If I want to send a letter or a package
from my house to my parents house,
there's certain things
that I need to put on that package
in order for it to get to the destination.
Right.
And that's the whole idea,
is that if I have a standard way
of doing that,
I can address an envelope that it goes in.
The message is inside the envelope
or inside the box,
that it's a standard size, that it's
that I don't just hand over,
a handful of stuff to the postal worker
and say, hey, deliver
this to, you know, my parents,
if I can be crazy, if you do that.
So there are some common
things that we need to do,
in order to make this work.
So we use a layered approach where
I can talk about, how all this stuff
fits together, and we need to organize it
so that, we can at least,
get packets from point
A, host A to host B and back.
So let's talk
let's talk about the different layers.
So there's, there's lots of different
people are going to go there.
And there are seven layers to the IP
stack. Yes.
Theoretical layers. Let's talk about that.
Let's talk about what's what's real
and happening out there together.
There's really four with the fifth
one that I call physical bits on the wire.
All right
I'm physically moving bits at the wire.
But let's start at the top of the stack.
The top of the stack
is the application layer.
So here I'm
supporting network applications.
So here are my transfer protocols
FTP, SMTp, Http.
Those are those are those.
That means there's a common envelope.
As my envelope there's a common
set of packages that are out there.
That I'm going to put my, information in.
So there's your envelope,
there's the transport.
How is it going to get there,
whether it's TCP or UDP.
Those are the big, data
transfer protocols, that are out there.
That's process to process protocol.
This would be, analogous to, what's the
oh that everything
is going to, go in a,
Postal service, track.
There you go.
That's how I'm transferring
information in that Postal Service truck
or on an airplane.
There's common ways of getting
the information from point A to point B
network IP routing.
This is,
how I'm, getting from point A to point B.
This would be addresses.
Right. So a street address.
And if you look, it's,
a number on your street,
your street name, your city,
your providence for state, your country.
We have the same things.
We are in network protocols.
There's I IPv4 and IPv6,
one that has,
we started running out of addresses.
Those are those four numbers.
8.8.8 for Google, you know.
128 101 87 I can I still remember
I still remember my old,
IP addresses for when I was in college,
like, last millennium.
It's amazing. Right?
But those
addresses there are,
is that network routing diagrams, right.
That tells me where it is. Right?
It tells me, which general area
and then, more specific, more specific
to how you get to the last number.
The,
the new IP, versions give us trillions
quadrillion, different addresses.
We ran out of the,
the old the old way of doing it,
which was for, for a bit numbers.
Now it's it's much larger than that.
So we're in good shape.
Then the next one is the data transfer
between neighboring networks.
What?
How am I, connected together?
Right.
Between the different networks,
that would be Ethernet 802
11, which is Wi-Fi, PGP
and things like that.
And that's that's really it.
So because these are standardized,
I have an easy way
that I can move data from one host
to another across multiple networks,
and that that
routing number in the network
is, is highly critical,
because that's how I know where to start
routing things.
I could say, hey, I'm on the 128,
network.
Oh, I, I got 128 over here.
Send that to me.
And then it it boils down that way.
It's actually pretty cool.
All right.
There's some cloud protocols
that are all based on Http or Https.
Web protocols.
That's how most of the cloud APIs
are built on, including our Rest interface
that we've talked about in
previous lectures and new protocols like,
MCP model context protocol
that we're seeing happen with a genetic
I they're all still built
on top of a RESTful, interface,
which is built on top of Http,
which is the application layer.