Okay, I want to talk about some things
to consider
when you're working in the cloud.
In some respects.
The cloud is like,
CPU in some respects, right?
I've got my processor,
which could be my host,
and I've got data
that's spread all over the place.
And just like a CPU where maybe
I don't have the data readily available,
and it has to do page faults and handle
page swapping and all that.
I've got even a bigger problem
when I talk about internet,
when I send out a request,
when I send a packet,
how do I know it
actually arrived on the other end?
This could be a problem where when I'm
requesting data, I send it back out.
I'm expecting a response back.
I need to handle this
appropriately. Right.
So and then also I need to look at that.
My internet may be my bottleneck
especially.
It's much slower
going over the internet than going
just on the IO
bus inside my, my computer itself.
So packets if I send a lot of packets out.
Right.
They get queued and they get, sent out
and then routers
can some time buffer information as well.
And can I rely on that router
that I've sent the stuff
to, to, not lose my data.
And sometimes they do.
And sometimes there's slowness
because that router's overwhelmed.
And there could be, packet delay.
So that's why some of this happens, right?
These routers are processing
a lot of packets.
It's saying, hey.
Oh, this guy wants this, information.
I know it's on router number five.
I'll send it over there.
But if that router is getting, you know,
millions and billions of packets.
A minute,
how how is it going to handle that?
Right?
So it keeps them up,
it buffers them and and keeps going along.
Sometimes they have
about highly redundant systems in there.
But these these routers are fine
tuned to do network, network routing.
Right.
But they still you can still lose data
and you can still have delays.
All right.
Reason, other reasons for losses
and delays.
The best way to think of it is,
is, this concept here,
I've got nodal
processing is what it's called.
Nodal processing includes,
d proc Dhcp trans and d prop.
So that that's the propagation
is the last one.
The d proc is nodal processing.
How much time does it take,
for the processor
on that router to check er bits,
determine the output link and then it
that that's what it does.
It's typically pretty quick.
But like I said before,
if I run into issues I get d q right.
If, I get dq'd
that's like a swimming term,
I get, I get stuck in the queue,
which means I'm waiting for the output
link, for transmission and depends
on how much congestion there is.
Right.
And then, d trans
is how long does it take to transmit.
And then propagation.
Propagation is probably the longest
but it could be queuing.
It could be queue time.
Especially if I'm overwhelmed.
All right.
So how is this relayed to the cloud?
Just remember, when you're working in a
in a cloud, especially in public clouds.
You've got a lot of other,
tenants that are running
on the same machine
and on the same network
hitting the same router,
which means you have the concept of noisy
neighbor, which we've talked about
in previous lectures.
Noisy neighbor means I've got someone else
that's they're running
similar things or running different things
doesn't matter.
But it's hitting
the router could be slowing things down.
And if the router becomes overwhelmed,
it can lose packets.
Ideally they don't, but
we're talking billions
and billions of packets a day.
It's kind of lose some of them.
So you have to make sure
when you are, working with cloud services
that you have retry
and that you have some kind of guarantees
that the other side
got what you expected them to get.