In this lecture we're going to talk about
cloud computing,
its history, its motivations,
and why we have it today.
So motivating scenario.
First off, the internet in the 1990s
was just blossoming.
There's a big.com boom at the time
and how small businesses
wanted to use the new internet
and things like that.
And but these services
needed computing power
and they network and storage
and all these things a lot.
There were a lot of incubators
that started at that time, really fast
anywhere
because I had a startup in the 1990s and,
I got some incubation funds
and they gave me servers that I could use.
That was awesome.
I could host my website there.
And that was to like an IBM incubator,
if I remember.
Right.
And there were a lot of these going on,
but the capital expenditure
was pretty high.
Right. And then someone
had to manage those servers.
So it cost us money to hire
someone to manage those servers.
And so there was a lot of short term risk
and capital risks
that you had to invest upfront.
And that's why you had a lot of companies
in the early 90s during the.com boom,
that were investing in infrastructure.
And a lot of infrastructure companies
came out of that.
And but at the same time, I just bought,
you know, maybe I buy a $50,000 server.
I'm not using it all the time.
So that's a wasted operational resource
right there on my wall.
That kind of stinks. Right?
So in the 90s, we started seeing,
some interesting things
bubble up around cloud computing.
So the desired
solution that people wanted
was that entrepreneurs
and small businesses
could use and lease resources.
That was that incubation,
kind of thing that was going on.
They could, lease resources and use those,
as they needed
instead of worrying about, buying them
and maintaining them, they could focus on
what was important for them,
which is which is important
as a small business focus is everything.
And so that was that was key at the time.
Also.
It would be great
if your physical devices weren't
physically located with you,
because then you could do
a true internet company
where you could reside anywhere.
You didn't have to physically
touch your servers and things like that.
So that was another desire as,
as people were starting to, to,
grow in that 90s, early 2000 things.
So all these desired solutions,
all the pent up pressure there
kind of drove more and more of,
the adoption of cloud technology.
So were out there.
So here's some key properties
from a Berkeley paper, that's out there,
on cloud computing.
I needed something that, and I was
I was involved in the global grid form
at the time,
global grid form
was all about high performance computing
and created some of the largest,
high performance computing,
clusters in the world
with well over a million nodes.
Some of you may have even participated
in setting at home.
The whole concept was, is,
let's take all these idle compute cycles
that are sitting out there,
and let's use them for something,
sitting at home was,
search for extraterrestrial life.
And, and I'm sure everyone had that
little,
screensaver up that was crunching numbers
all across the world.
That same concept kind of,
let itself into cloud computing
from the 90s of sharing resources
for high performance
computing across millions of nodes to now.
Hey, what about enterprise
organizations that had a lot of capacity,
but they had burst of of, of need.
Great.
The best example of this is Amazon, right?
Amazon was growing,
but most of their transactions
were happening in November and December.
So what do you do with all those
spare cycles the rest of the year.
So that those are the sorts of things
that, started happening?
All right.
So, another thing that happened,
during the 90s and early 2000
was, the browser and the whole concept
of the thin client and the web
really started to, to bubble up,
which was, which was very, very important.
Right?
What it meant that,
I didn't have to have a big beefy box
at home or on my desk at work.
Instead,
I use more of a browser or thin client,
and I access big servers on the back end
that did all the hard work.
Well, this lends itself well to to cloud.
Technology too.
So these are all really interesting,
concepts
that kind of contributed
to the adoption of cloud.
All right.
So let's take a look
at the newest definition of cloud.
Because if we want to really look at,
cloud.
And I remember when this, when, cloud
computing was first coined
back in the early 2000,
I remember I was sitting in Edinburgh
at a open grid forum
or Global Grid Forum conference, and,
a guy
from, Amazon said,
hey, we're going to take some of the stuff
we've been talking about
and using and high performance computing.
And, I'm going to try and do that
on our infrastructure
in, at Amazon because, hey,
I got all these spare cycles, and I said,
I'll use some of those spare cycles
any time.
And, they, they came up with this
really cool concept of cloud
computing different than grid computing,
which is what we were doing.
The whole concept of grid computing
was like it was a utility.
So he upped the game to cloud computing,
which was really interesting.
But if we look at the definition of cloud
computing, the key things you want to,
see here is that cloud computing is this
model that, lets me,
ubiquitously
access network storage and compute
almost like I plug in to a power outlet.
I don't care where it's at.
I just care that it works.
And that's that's all I really care about,
is that it works.
Right? And that I can rapidly provision
the resources
I need to get my compute done.
And, and there's several different,
and we'll talk about
the essential characteristics and,
and service models
that, that are available.
And there's more service models
we're starting to see emerge.
All right.
Let's look at the definition.
Let's parse it out a little bit.
Model. Right.
It's an abstract of the framework,
that is enabling the following technology
ubiquity,
which means it can come from anywhere.
It's pervasive.
It's everywhere convenient.
This is critical that I can easily spin up
and tear down
what I need to get my job
done, and I can do it on demand.
I can't say, oh, I'm going to provision
this and wait, 2 or 3 weeks
or 3 or 4 months to get the resources
I need to do my job.
That's the old way
that things used to work.
Actually, in the data centers,
you'd write up a full, business plan
on why you needed the equipment.
You had network architectures,
you had all that stuff.
And then, proposal would go in.
A budget would be approved
in three months later, you'd get servers,
to run your website.
That's how it used to work.
Now I can go in and quickly,
over the internet,
I can quickly provision
a web server in a matter of,
30s. Maybe a minute.
And I'm off to the races.
Okay.
Resources.
Another interesting, verb in there.
A variety of different resources.
And we're seeing new resources here.
Storage network, compute accelerators
and, and some other interesting resources
that we're starting to see.
AI is resource, other tools
and platforms as a resource,
which we'll get into in a little bit.
Also, the other concept here
that's very different from cloud,
from grid computing is cloud
computing said there was
a shared pool of resources
with grid computing.
I had a shared pool,
but it was allocated to me
for a certain period of time.
With cloud computing, I have a shared pool
and I'm sharing the resource
with other people all the time now.
You can't get dedicated resources,
but you're still sharing network.
You're still sharing things like that.
All right.
So that's that's important to understand.
The other thing that's important
in cloud is configurability.
So that I can take a machine,
I can install the OS
I want on it, I can configure it the way
I want with users and all that stuff.
Very different from great computing,
where it's a set of,
operating systems
that are already on there. You,
ran jobs on that operating system
with cloud computing.
I'm actually running a virtual machine.
Right.
I have a full operating system on there.
Instead of just running an individual job,
I'm running a full
operating system.
Okay, the other really important thing
was this whole concept of rapidly the,
deploying and provisioning when I need it.
Now, we've seen, problem recently in this,
specifically in, instances that are,
in high demand, the waiting queues
can be up to three weeks right now
in a lot of the cloud service providers
that are out there.
But that's, normally not the case.
The other important thing is that
it would be minimal management required.
So all the management,
the physical management of the devices
are outside of my control now,
but I can easily pre-provision machines
and get them spun up quickly
with little, management effort at all.
That's the whole idea behind it.
Okay,
here's the five essential characteristics
on demand service,
broadband
network access, resource pooling.
And the resource pooling has a lot to do
with the business model
more than anything else.
I will talk about that.
And then, rapid elasticity
where I can scale up
and scale down quickly
and then that I it's measurable service
so that I'm able to see
how much I am using,
how much it's cost to me and the
performance that I'm getting out of it.