In a previous lecture, we
talked about cloud computing in general.
Let's talk about the enablers.
What really happened
to make this really, thrive
and why it's so ubiquitous today.
So to go there, we got to go back.
Let's go back in history.
And now you're going to hear Darren,
our doctor, Darren,
wax eloquently about the times in the 90s,
the great 90s, right, in Silicon Valley.
I happened to be in an organization
that, was taking advantage of cloud
computing before it was called cloud
computing was called grid computing,
which was all about high performance
computing.
And there were, standard body
that I was a part of.
I was a chairman
of a couple working groups.
And, it was really cool
because we had academia and business
all working together
to see how we could take, computers
that were scattered all over the world
and have them work together to solve
problems, which was really, really cool.
And not only all
over the world, but then we also looked
at high performance computers
that, you know, for
the first time were doing,
terabyte,
you know, terabytes of data.
It was crazy, right?
At the time, we thought it was so cool.
We're doing teraflops.
Wow. We're so fast now.
We're talking x of flops today.
But grid computing was the foundation
of cloud computing where it has today.
In the early 2000, we saw that
there were some limitations
to, cloud computing.
They were great for batch processing,
for doing,
simulations of weather, nuclear
explosions, and lots of other, you know,
high, security things
for government and energy and research.
But how can I use that for my, day
to day work?
And that's where where,
we had to really start looking at things.
And remember
I mentioned in, in other courses,
great computing
focused on running individual jobs
and enterprises.
They do run jobs, but they run
applications in the whole ecosystems.
And and their workflows are very complex
compared to high performance computing
where the workflows are, much simpler,
maybe 5 or 6 steps.
But I need to run it a million times.
Right?
So that's that's a big difference
between the two.
Okay.
In the mid 2000s,
the whole concept, cloud concept evolved
from the grid computing into
now let's take a look.
And with the advent of virtualization
things started,
you know, really happening.
And it means that I could spin up
these VMs
instead of running individual jobs,
I could run a VM on this machine.
And things like that started
happening in 2006.
AWS launches, however, Amazon launches
Amazon Web Services.
They even call Amazon Cloud.
At the time,
it was, say, Amazon Web Services.
And what was really
cool about this in the beginning is
I could have
I could take that virtualization concept
and the grid concept
and mesh them together.
And I could go easily spin up
instances of my infrastructure
on someone else's infrastructure,
which was really cool.
And then I only paid
for how much I used it.
Right. And so that was that was huge.
And then from there
that's called infrastructure as a service.
We'll get into that
a little bit more detail.
But from there that we started
seeing platforms as a service
and then software as a service.
So I didn't even need to buy licenses
for software, I didn't need to manage it.
I could just buy a VM that had
the licensing, had everything on it.
I could spin that up, run
my stuff, and I was off to the races.
So this really decrease the amount of time
it took for me
to build up the infrastructure
and deploy the software and manage that.
That could all happen.
And someone
else's infrastructure was very cool and.
All right, so let's take a look at the
at the real history.
Let's get down into the nitty gritty.
In the early days of shared, utility
or grid computing, there were a couple key
players, Sun Grid engine.
So Sun Microsystems had a killer product.
Sun Grid Engine
or Sun Grid was the free version.
Sun grid engine.
You could rent space from Sun Microsystems
on these really fast at the time.
Really fast. Servers.
And I was charged by the CPU
time.
So if my job was sitting there idle,
I didn't get I didn't get dinged,
I didn't have to pay for it,
but I paid for CPU time.
This was very similar
to what had been done with mainframes.
This sounds a lot like mainframes.
I used to be able to rent time on a
mainframe, and I got charged for CPU time.
That's how much time is my process
actually using the CPU?
There were others
that were in this as well.
HPE Utility
data Center, IBM on Demand computing,
DSA was another one.
And then one of my favorite ones
was sitting at home
and said he, was actually super,
super cool.
I actually got to watch,
the control center said at home was,
totally awesome, but said he at home
was the search for extraterrestrial life.
And they use people's laptops
and, and there was a sweaty running board,
a leaderboard who was giving
the most cycles to find this stuff.
So all you did
was you installed this little piece
of software on your laptop,
and, it ran a screensaver.
And then in the background
it would download data
from a central repository and then
crunch on that data on your laptop
and then send the results back.
Kind of scary when you think about it.
Oh, someone's downloading
data on my computer using my CPU,
generating new data
and then sending that data back out.
I was kind of crazy that we let people do
that.
Companies I it was crazy.
At the height of it, companies
were on the leaderboard.
Companies would set up, all machines
to just run steady at home
and, so they could be
on the top of the leaderboard.
It was, it was, it was a, it was a thing
back in the 90s and early 2000,
that kind of went away
because people were worried
about cyber security all of a sudden, oh,
I have someone else's software
running on my box,
receiving and sending data back and forth.
I love Little Fishy. Right?
So people were worried about that.
Okay.
Before AWS hosting,
some some things started to merge,
very similar to what AWS does today.
Loud cloud.
Rackspace managed hosting
did virtualize things
Inca and then Enki, and then Intel cloud.
Intel have one of the first cloud
cloud services that were out there
where you could actually deploy VMs
and run them and all that,
that Intel engineers actually helped
Amazon
build up, build up their solution. Right.
There were, some others, Sun Grid, Google,
had early
stuff there and so did Microsoft.
But AWS did something really interesting.
And to understand what they did, let's
talk about how anybody else got started.
Doctor Werner Vogels
I know him personally.
I worked with him in the open grid forum.
He gets hired by Amazon
to help to build up cloud computing,
architecture to handle the bursting
workloads that happened
during the Christmas rush at Amazon,
which is November to December.
They had infrastructure, but it wasn't
being used highly effectively.
And why not go to cloud
computing or grid computing?
Because grid computing was really good
at handling really large,
massively parallel amounts of of work.
So Warner,
he, he did a lot of research in this area
and worked, with us in global
grid form quite a bit.
And, he took a lot of,
his research and learning and teaching
Amazon and, created what is today Amazon.
AWS, Amazon
Web Services, which is really,
really cool.
Now, one thing that was different
about Amazon, what they did
was they first
got their own house in order.
How can I handle running all all of these,
capacity bursting
that happens during November and December.
And they figured that out
and they said, hey,
what do we do with all these spare cycles?
We have the rest of the ten months
out of the year.
Why don't we do something
like steady at home?
Why don't we do like what we're starting
to see with grid sun grid engine,
where you tell me where I can rent CPU's,
from, Amazon during all that time.
So Amazon could recoup some of the cost
that it took to manage and to run,
their data centers.
So that's brilliant. Right.
Here's
where things got really interesting.
They, they decided
instead of charging for CPU time,
because that's the only thing
that people were really charging for.
They were going to charge for network
and storage and CPU,
but instead of charging, absolutely.
How much you were using on the CPU,
they decided to charge for wall
clock time.
So how long has your,
have has your VM been running,
whether it's running or not,
how long have you had it installed?
Now, this is brilliant
because not everyone uses their,
their VMs in Amazon all the time.
And a lot of people,
they were actually polluting,
polluting the data center
with all these zombie,
virtual machines
that were running out there.
Right.
So that's a problem
when you've got all these on
because you're taking up resources.
But no one was paying for those resources
in the old model, in this new model,
you paid for the resources.
Because you're you're using up memory
and things like that.
And, but you're not using the CPU.
But I'm still going to charge you
for having that sitting there
using some of the resources.
So that's that's pretty cool, right?
Warnock took that business model
and ran with it
and became the cloud evangelist.
Right.
The cloud the whole cloud concept
started with Warner.
It was super cool right?
He became the CTO of Amazon
Global Evangelist.
He started showing up to the Global grid
forums touting cloud, cloud, cloud.
And then there was the starting
of a whole bunch of cloud conferences.
That continue today.
Which is, which is really cool.
So the thing that made this viable,
that didn't make grid computing
as viable as a consumer,
we still use grid computing
and all the high performance computing
clusters out there is that concept.
Still, there are still valuable,
very valuable in research.
But the business model
made this highly profitable for Amazon
because I started charging for,
wall clock time instead of just CPU time.
That was the big, big one.
They also charge for storing data
and moving data in and out of their cloud.
Right.
Which everyone knows the egress costs.
Moving data out of the cloud costs
more cost nothing to move it in the cloud.
But retrieving and getting out costs
substantial.
Right.
So this business model made it
so that, they could grow, right?
They could invest more.
And everyone was getting a lot of value
out of it.
Right?
Because I didn't have to go spend millions
of dollars building a data center.
I could lease space from Amazon
at a very reduced cost, initial cost,
and which made it great for startups
and businesses
that were doing a digital transformation
but didn't have the knowhow
or didn't have the capital to spend on it.
All right.
What this meant was that Amazon,
if I spun up
in, a VM on a individual box,
they could optimize their CPU utilization,
dramatically by taking those VMs
that weren't being used
and just suspending them, not having them,
you know, having them in
virtual memory instead of in real memory
and setting those aside.
So you had multiple people
running on the same, box,
which increased utilization
of the hardware.
And everything's everything's great all
around, decreasing amount of power used.
All that stuff happened through
this, which was pretty cool.
All right.
Out of this became three basic service
models.
There's actually more models
that have been built after that.
But let's talk about the three basic
service models,
at the top, software as a service.
So as I mentioned, before, software
as a service is something like,
Google Cloud or Google
Calendar, Google Docs,
SAP in AWS,
SAP Hana,
that software as a service type of thing.
And a lot of people move to it. Workday.
People saw that a lot of companies
went to this model, right.
Because it meant that,
the software providers could easily manage
software for you.
You paid for it.
For, the use that you made every,
every month.
Typically you rented it for a month,
and then it
it made it much more flexible
for the consumer as well.
So highly valuable.
Netflix is another great
example of software as a service, right?
I mean, everyone uses Netflix.
I use that service.
I'm not I'm not paying to host machine.
I'm not paying to host, videos
on my servers.
I'm using Netflix to do that.
And there's additional services
that come from it.
If you go the step below this, the next
one is called platform as a service.
So platform as a service is used a lot of
times by independent software vendors.
S fees
because they want to host, they want to
host their software as a service.
But platform as a service means, hey,
there's infrastructure
set up there for me to do it.
Build servers, a lamp stack,
which is, a Linux, web.
It's like a web server.
That's the best way to think of it.
It's a web server with a backend database,
but there's lots of other really cool
platforms as a service that,
decrease the
complexity of setting up my own
infrastructure,
to, host my own software type thing.
Right.
So this is software that's sitting there
that makes it easier
to host software and manage software
and things like that.
Lots of examples out there.
And then underneath
that is the one that I started with,
which is infrastructure as a service
or IaaS as, as you'll hear before,
this is spinning up
VMs, network storage, right.
Infrastructure that I run my software on.
Right.
New models are coming out
like function as a service,
I as a service, blah blah blah.
As I say, the list goes on and on,
and we'll talk about some of those
other models in other lectures.
Okay.
Best way to look at the service models
I love this,
this whole concept, this diagram,
if I look at software as a service,
it has applications, data, runtime
middleware, OS virtualization,
all the the whole stack done
platform as a service means that
I'm going to manage my applications
and my data, but everything else
underneath the covers is managed for me
by somebody else.
Okay, infrastructure as a service
goes all the way down to the OS layer,
right?
So infrastructure as a service means I'm
going to give you all the virtualization
server storage network.
I'm going to manage
OS, middleware,
runtime data and applications.
So this diagram really shows you
that the simplicity of these models.
Right.
And and who's responsible for what.
Okay.
As we see all these things
kind of building up,
you can see that
the consumer on the back end,
can either pay Amazon for software
as a service.
Amazon has some software out there
at Google does right.
And AWS or Microsoft does.
Oracle does.
And I pay more for software as a service
than I pay for platform as a service
and infrastructure as a service,
but they all build on top of each other.
So platform as a service builds
on top of infrastructure
software
as a service builds on top of platform.
I can consume at any layer that I want,
but the value increases as I go up
the value chain and so does the cost.
Okay,
we've talked about the different modes.
Let's talk about deployment models.
When we think of cloud
we always think of public cloud.
But in reality there's lots of different
deployment models.
There's a private cloud.
So I can take the same concepts
that were developed at AWS
and Google and Intel
and you know, Microsoft.
I can bring those into my own data center.
Now people go, well, Darren,
you already mentioned that,
hey, we go to cloud because I don't need
the capital expenditure.
But as your company grows,
you have to look at the price,
performance and price cost analysis.
It might be cheaper for you
to actually buy machines
and run your own private cloud,
where you're not renting
your equipment out to someone else,
but you're managing it in the way
the clouds are managed.
So everything is self-service
and things and things like that.
You can run that totally on prem.
Then we have the concept
of community clouds,
which have taken taken root
in some in some industries.
Maybe I don't want my cloud accessible
by everyone.
So I want to create my own community
cloud where I'm sharing with,
let's say it's, medical facility, right?
And maybe a medical, group. I've got,
Community Cloud
here where I've got several different
organizations contributing to a cloud
and managing that cloud.
These are these didn't turn out as popular
as I thought they might.
Public cloud we've already talked about.
This is global.
There's, you know, I can use it anywhere.
The area that we're moving into
now is this hybrid cloud which says,
I've got a private cloud and
I'm going to use a public cloud together.
And these architectures
are really interesting.
And they give you the best of both worlds.
I can invest and keep all of my
private data
and all my security in my private cloud,
and I can use a public cloud
for bursting in different types
of applications over there.
So this gives me that flexibility
of moving my,
workloads between private and public cloud
based off of different criteria,
whether it's, compliance criteria or it
could be cost, whatever the case may be.
And then the penultimate
of all of this
would be the multi hybrid cloud,
where now my workloads can move
across multiple public
clouds across multiple private clouds
and even community clouds.
And we're going to talk about those,
those different architectures,
during this course.