Okay.
In this lecture we're
going to talk about obstacles
and opportunities for cloud computing.
This is really important to understand
what these are and how to overcome these.
And and we're going to talk about
why it's important in computer science
to build architectures that are flexible
so that you can move into these multi
hybrid cloud types of architectures
to overcome some of these obstacles.
So let's cool.
Let's let's I drive in.
There's a lot of
the first one is availability.
There have been very well-documented,
outages, including on my podcast,
the AWS, Thanksgiving outage of 2020,
major outage on AWS.
And, people lost billions of dollars,
during that outage,
when you put everything into a public
cloud, they have issues sometimes.
And even though they've,
they're some of the best in the world for,
you know, managing data centers,
they're they've got a lot of clients.
So things do happen.
It is important to understand
that when they do that,
you need to be able to have a backup plan,
whether it's moving to a different cloud
or a different region in a cloud
or moving on on prem.
So availability issues
is something that's a big deal, right?
When I when
I was a CIO and we ran our data center,
we had a goal of three
nights, 99.9% uptime.
The cloud service
providers are nowhere near that.
In fact, in some organizations
they want 4 or 5 nines uptime.
If you have a, highly critical system,
when you have downtime, it causes
bodily harm or things like that, or,
you know, financial loss.
You can't afford to be
in these public clouds
where they're downtimes are in about 98%.
And in a lot of cases, it means
you're going to have to have a resilient,
architecture to handle those outages.
And what are you going to do with it?
The concepts around cloud computing
should enable you
to increase
that to, 5 or 6 nines very easily.
Okay.
Another thing that we need to worry about,
that people worry about is vendor lock in.
If I'm using, APIs from AWS
and I decide, hey, AWS is tight,
cost me too much,
and I want to move to, Azure,
or I want to move to Oracle or whatever.
Or maybe Oracle's got a new service
I want to use.
If I'm stuck using their APIs
and it's not portable,
I need to be worried about that.
Right.
So it's enticing
because they'll do everything for me.
But at the same time, I then lose my,
ability to move.
Another big cost
and vendor lock in is egress costs.
This is moving data out of the cloud,
which can be very expensive.
So I got to watch all these things
when I get stuck into a cloud.
We call that the Hotel California
from the Eagle Song Hotel California,
which is I can check my data in,
but I can't get it out
and it's too expensive to move it.
You got to be worried about these things.
So you have to watch for these things
in your architectures and in the
way that you deploy.
And as
for other real quick ones,
there's a lot lack of trust
if you have, data that is highly critical.
Maybe it's, you work in government.
Am I going to put my data up?
That's top secret into a cloud?
Probably not, because I don't know
who has access to that.
Who has access to the machines?
Can they walk up to the machine,
plug in a USB key,
or get information off that machine
somehow?
Security threats are a huge deal.
So I've got to work on security,
and we're going to talk a lot
about the shared security model,
in these courses
and what that means and who's responsible
for what on security.
Virtualization is is a good solution.
But there's some downsides to it
that we'll talk about.
Some of those downsides were noisy
neighbor downsides, but also, speed.
There's some speed here for some of the
virtualization techniques were out there.
And then also, since you're not
in full control of all the hardware,
it could be a bad configuration
in firmware or the hardware.
That's not unleashing
all of the power of silicon.
That might be under the covers
that you could take advantage of.
And so those are some other obstacles.
Let's talk about data movement
as another, big, problem
that I need to look at.
Data is very expensive to move around,
so I need to be very careful
where I'm placing my data
and making sure that,
my data is not being shipped
inadvertently around.
Great example of this is a customer.
I won't name who they are
that I've worked with in the past.
They set up a HPC cluster part
in the cloud in part not in the cloud.
And one thing that anyone that works
with HPC clusters know
is that data is king in high performance
computing, so moving data
from the individual nodes into central
repositories is very important.
In moving
data back and forth is important.
They inadvertently burn through
their whole cloud budget by putting
two nodes
in their HPC cluster in the cloud,
and they're very chatty, so they're moving
data back and forth, back and forth.
And it, it it costs a lot of money
and, and burn through their whole year
budget in a month and a half.
So that's that's a big problem.
Here's the other one.
We call it the noisy neighbor problem.
And the best way to explain noisy
neighbor is,
the way that cloud, as we talked in
previous lectures, cloud takes advantage
of multiple people on the same machine
running on the same VMs.
And if one VM is not currently being used,
it's put into,
you know, virtual memory
instead of real memory.
It's still using some resources,
but and maybe it's
not using a lot of CPU, or maybe it's
using a lot of network bandwidth.
These things, the resources
that they're using,
has an impact on your performance.
You see this a lot in,
applications that, have the time
bound to them where there's a quality
of service or SLA that, hey, this job
that I'm running needs to run within 30s,
but the variability could be 10s 30s
a minute and a half.
Whatever the case may be.
That's because a noisy neighbor,
another good way of describing noisy
neighbor is, the difference
between renting in an apartment complex,
a big, huge apartment complex, or owning
your own home in a apartment complex.
If your neighbor above you is being really
loud, playing the music loud, whatever
until the wee hours of the morning,
you pound on the ceiling with your broom.
You call the super.
The super goes,
yeah, I'll tell you what I can say.
Whatever that's like in the cloud.
If I'm at home and I've got ten kids.
So if my kids are being loud, all I have
to do is go and talk to them directly.
And if they
if they're if they're, you know, I'm
trying to record
a podcast or something or lecture
and they're still being loud.
I can restrict them right?
I can say,
you know what, you're in your room
or you know what, go outside and play.
Or you know, send them to a movie
or something like that.
That's the same thing
in your own data center.
If you're running a private cloud,
you can quarantine people.
You can decrease the amount of resources
that they have
because you have access to that.
So that's that noisy neighbor
or predictive performance,
scale, storage scale.
You know what?
This this is a, a big a potential problem.
But for private clouds, it's
an issue if you're running out of, storage
in the cloud,
it seems like there's unlimited storage.
But as you know, as you move into the
petabytes, getting access to that storage
and the cost of that storage, depends
on the different tiers that you have.
So you have to understand your storage.
You can't just say,
I'll just throw it all into an S3 bucket.
You got to be smart about it,
because you want to make sure that you're,
getting the, the most value
out of what you're doing,
that you're not storing things
in expensive storage
when it can go in a glacial
storage type of thing.
Distributed systems and debugging.
This is very important.
When you are working on
distributed systems
and trying to debug systems,
it's much harder to figure out
where the bugs are residing,
in which application or microservice
they're residing in, or is it a problem
in data, or is there a network pick up?
All these things have a play.
So it is very, very important
that you put in place,
different techniques
for distributed distributed
bugging and distributed system
monitoring, logging and things like that.
And reproducing bugs at scale
can be a real hard thing.
And, and this is something
that, takes time to learn how to do.
And hopefully, through these lectures,
we'll, we'll learn some techniques
that will help.
Instance,
scaling up and down can be hard at times.
Cloud makes it much easier,
but it can take time for VMs to spin up.
It could take 4 or 5 minutes.
And if
I get a big huge burst in my website,
you know, I got to be able to handle that.
So, there are some techniques
that we can use, to do this.
If you're in your own data center
running this,
this could be problematic as well
if I don't have any more servers to do it.
So this is where that multi hybrid cloud
comes in where I can burst into the cloud.
I have some things ready to go
and I'm a little preemptive.
This is a another trade off
between cost and response.
And responsiveness
of of your applications.
All right.
Sharing resources.
Here's another, another problem
that we've seen in the past.
If I'm sharing resources, or
there can be some,
some issues around data.
And if there are issues in the cloud, like
if Amazon has an outage,
who's liable for that?
Right.
And what
kind of agreement do you have with them?
Especially if it's a critical system.
You know, what's going to happen there.
So you are remember, you are sharing
resources with someone else.
So in in major outages,
Delta has had these.
You know, I just had these where they're
in the cloud whose reputation is soiled.
If AWS goes down and united
using them or target
have a big target using Amazon stuff.
But or Azure
if that goes down and all of a sudden
your website's down,
who's whose reputation is at stake.
So you you can architect things
so that things stay up,
but you've got to architect things.
It just doesn't happen automatically.
Software licensing has been an issue
in, and an obstacle in adopting cloud.
As I spin up more and more instances,
the whole licensing software
licensing paradigm has shifted.
And how do I how do I licensing?
Do I license it per VM?
Do I license it per physical device?
There's a whole bunch of things
that have happened in this space
and continue to change over time.
All right.
So let's talk about,
these obstacles that we've come up with
and some opportunities.
Right.
So availability and business continuity
I'm gonna
I'm going to use multiple clouds.
So this is the multi hybrid
cloud concept data
lock in getting my data stuck in things.
All right.
Let's work on a data architecture.
Let's use some standard APIs.
So that I'm not locked into one vendor
that I can move
my workloads around moving data around.
I've got to, understand and deploy that
data confidentiality and auditability
make sure you are, deploying encryption.
Make sure that you have the keys.
Not that AWS has the keys.
They will they will gladly create the keys
for you and keep them.
You should be doing that yourself.
Make sure that you're setting up
VLANs and firewalls and all that stuff.
You're still responsible for this, stuff.
Don't rely on the cloud
service providers for for all of that.
Believe it or not, sometimes moving data,
it's cheaper to just Fedex
data, which sounds horrible,
but if I have terabytes of data
or petabytes of data, I can store them
on terabyte drives and ship them
from one data center to another,
sometimes faster than using the internet.
Which is crazy, but that does happen.
There's lots of different techniques
for data.
Data transfer bottlenecks.
Let's take a look at all of them.
What should be interesting,
performance unpredictability.
If you have workloads that you need highly
predictable performance,
look at running in private cloud
for those and public cloud for others.
Right.
And this will
this will give you, the ability
to fine tune your performance
on, on those clouds.
All right.
Scalable storage.
We've got to talk about, data
architectures and storage architectures.
There's a whole set of lectures,
based on that.
Let's look at,
debugging large distributed systems,
logging, auditability
all that will be important.
Including, repeatability.
Is, is, very important.
Also look at, scaling quickly.
There's lots of things that were invented
on autoscaling and preemptive scaling,
preemptive scaling, that are possibilities
there that we can look at
and then, reputation.
You know what?
This one's
this was going to be a tough one, right?
Because if you put all your eggs
in one basket
and that basket goes down and you go down,
this can be a big problem.
Right?
And we talked a little bit about software
licensing.
So lots of obstacles,
lots of great opportunities.
Especially for cloud architects.
This is where you earn your keep.