All right.
In this lecture we're going to
cover OpenStack and how it came about.
It's an open source.
They called open source
cloud OS for building IaaS.
And it really came out
from all the success that the public
cloud service providers had
and all the things that they were doing.
And also, with VMware, that was,
very popular at the time,
focusing on compute
and not just, just compute at first,
but then they needed something
that could do network and storage and,
all the other aspects of it, like all the
public cloud service providers had.
So OpenStack
actually took some of the best, tools
that were out there
that did the individual things
and kind of as a consortium
brought everything together and formed
something called the OpenStack Foundation.
And at first it was messy,
because you had a lot of, tool,
providers, all open source tool providers
that had their opinions
and they all did different things.
And so they wanted to get
the best of everything together
so that they could produce something
that could
allow, open source community
to stand up their own private cloud
on their own infrastructure,
and even stand up their own
regional clouds and compete
with all the big, players like Amazon,
and Azure and Google at the time.
And believe it or not, those guys
actually helped contribute to OpenStack
in some in some respects as well,
because they wanted the ability for people
to have both private and public decided
make it easier for the migration
of moving, between different clouds.
So let's take a look at some of the key
elements inside
and then key services
inside OpenStack. First off,
and these are in no
particular order,
not in the order that, they came in.
You could go look out on the OpenStack
Foundation on kind of, the, history of it.
It's a fascinating, history in,
in the emergence of cloud computing,
frankly.
So, it was interesting
when it was going through it
and sitting, you know, behind closed
doors, listening to the fighting over
just the naming of things
was fascinating at the time.
So let's go over a quick look at their,
first one, Keystone.
This is an identity manager
that helps with authentication,
multi-tenant projects
and role based access across,
private cloud that you're standing up.
Nova is my software
defined compute controller.
Glance is image, management.
So I can I can take a snapshot of a VM
and it's storing and managing my images
across, my cloud where Nova is
the cloud is the compute controllers
that takes those images
and turns them into, running VMs.
I've got neutron for my
software defined networking
and, cinder for block storage.
Which, gives me
those persistent volumes are attachable
to individual instances
and then Swift for my object storage
at very S3 bucket, style high durable
object storage.
Horizon four is my web interface.
So I could have a web interface
into doing all these things.
And horizon
obviously was built by the team
on bringing all these different projects,
together under one umbrella,
before each one of these projects
have their own user interface.
And the first versions of OpenStack were
a Frankenstein mess, to say the least.
And then there's heat,
which is a template driven deployment
from multi-service stacks.
This is very similar to cloud formations.
And, and, he can actually take
cloud for, formations.
So it's a very cool tool if I'm doing
multiple VMs, for my application.
Okay.
Let's take a look at,
how everything fits together.
Yeah. Really simply.
I've got a control node that's out there
that has the services running on it.
The the horizon dashboard,
which is my user interface,
identity management with Keystone,
the glance API.
Nova.
This is the control node, and there can be
multiple control nodes running,
in a, in a high availability cluster.
But these control nodes are important
for controlling all of the other,
physical devices
that are out there in your, private cloud.
Right.
And then I've got compute nodes, network
nodes, block storage
nodes, and,
and object storage, nodes as well.
So the physical devices
that are out there,
I need to know what those devices are and
also which services are running on them.
When you're deploying OpenStack, I think
the minimum you can really get away with,
you could run it on one, machine,
but that's not going to do you very much.
But I think the minimum you need for
the control plane is probably about
three nodes, and that that'll give you
a micro cloud right there.
Okay.
Installation.
So if you if you want to try this,
you can actually download and install this
starting on a single ubuntu host
like I already mentioned.
You can run it on, on there.
And it's really simple,
to get up and running,
you just install OpenStack tools
and then you can run an OpenStack
quickstart all in one, and it will store
all of the elements on there.
And then you can play around
with your own cloud on one box,
which, lets you look at the interface.
It really doesn't give you a lot
of benefit, except maybe for development,
maybe you're running some, Iirc,
some infrastructure is code
and you want to try things out
before you, deploy it on a big,
on a big cluster in boxes.
Okay.
No, multi-node production.
We've already kind of covered this
a little bit.
I need control over nodes.
Compute
nodes, storage nodes, and network nodes.
Those are the four types of nodes
that I need.
In order to deploy OpenStack,
you can actually use something
like OpenStack Ansible,
which will actually you can specify
which nodes are going to be what and
put it into your ansible, playbook there.
And voila, it will deploy it
and you're off to the races.
Now, someone has also done some other work
by, Kola Ansible,
where it's all containerized, where I'm
running OpenStack in a container,
or I can do 000, which is actually
pretty cool, where I'm running OpenStack
in OpenStack itself,
which is very interesting,
where I'm using a public
or I'm
using a cloud to run a cloud inside it.
You can even run OpenStack out there
on, public cloud if you wanted to.
If you want to, do that,
that could be kind of fun.
Fun to play around
with. But watch your cost.
All right.
Common workflow,
that you want to do
once you get things up and running, is
you want to create a project,
create users in there, create roles.
These are the basic things that you need
to do in order to get things running.
Remember, OpenStack
is you running your own cloud, right?
So you've got to set up users.
You've got a set of roles, projects
and put security around all those.
These are key aspects that you'll
want to do in order to get things running.
All right.
You also want to upload some
images in there so that you can use them.
So they give you the ability
to, take images that are available
and upload them into, OpenStack.
And then,
you want to be able to launch a VM
to see how it's working,
and then you'll have access to your VM.
So these are all command line interfaces.
You can do this via the horizon
which is their web interface as well.
But here's some good command
line interfaces for launching a VM.
I call OpenStack Server Create,
and I can tell you how big I want it.
The image I'm going to use, the network
I'm going to use a security group
and so on and so forth and give it a name.
All right.
I can then attach a volume to a specific,
server that I've already launched
where I'm going to create a volume,
and then I'm going to do the attaching.
This allows me to add more storage to VMs
that are already running.
If I need to.
Right.
And then I need
if I need to set up, different,
security groups and different IP addresses
and things like that.
There's an interface for all that as well.
All right.
If you don't want to do command
line interface and learn that
which most people don't want to at first,
what do they do?
They go to the web interface.
So the web interface is a horizon.
So this is where I can set up
I have a project
and I can set up compute instances
in those projects.
I can set up network in those projects.
I've got identity
for users and management.
And then I can use, orchestrate
multiple stacks as well.
So there's lots of different tools
available in there
that, you can go and explore yourself.
All right.
The best practices in using OpenStack
take advantage
of these great tools
that have been developed over the last.
Oh, I guess it's been almost 20 years, 15
to 20 years.
Like, heat, for repeatable,
version deployments of multiple,
application or multiple applications
or microservices running,
make sure that you, separate the roles
and isolate the,
APIs and the compute networks
and storage services.
Make sure you define roles appropriately
and then enable high availability
in your, open stack
so that you don't run into a problem
if you have a machine go down.
So if you're doing this for production,
or even testing
that you want more reliable,
make sure you have enough machines
and you've set things up appropriately.
Don't forget to monitor
what's going on with your public cloud
so that you can see when things start
going south, and make sure that you are
securing your endpoints with TLS
and establish some really good role
based access policies,
and also use network segmentation.
These are common,
key elements that you should be thinking
about for, security of your cloud.
So in summary, OpenStack
is like AWS for yourself or Azure
for yourself or Google for yourself.
They provide other services as well.
But guess what?
The OpenStack community is still alive
and well.
In fact, it's
highly used in Europe and Asia.
As you've got a great start
up and open source
kind of communities there.
And you can deploy it via quickstart.
It used to be a bear to deploy
because there were
so many services, you had to get set up
and you had to get the right
because people weren't using Iirc,
they were doing it by hand.
Now there's éac out there.
Infrastructure is code.
It's much easier to, use.
And then also if you need to do things
more dynamically, they have a great, API
and command line interface,
a rest API and a command line interface.
So you can easily
deploy and use these things.